He took a false oath on the Quran and deceived the Balochs and
कुरान की झूठी कसम खाई और बलोचों को धोखे
called them down and captured them.  And this is where
से नीचे बुला के पकड़ लिया। और यहीं पे
Jinnah was made the legal advisor of Kalat and it proved so
जिन्ना को कलात का लीगल एडवाइजर बनाना ऐसा
costly
भारी पड़ा
that he got angry because natural gas was
कि अब वो भड़क गए क्योंकि नेचुरल गैस
extracted from Balochistan but was
निकली बलोचिस्तान से लेकिन निकाल के
sent to Karachi, Lahore and Rawalpindi.  How a
कराची, लाहौर और रावलपिंडी भेज दी गई। एक
single 80 year old Baloch Nawab Nauroz Khan
अकेला 80 साल का बलोच नवाब नौरोज़ खान ने
single-handedly created a storm in the entire area.
अकेले कैसे पूरे एरिया में तूफान मचा
But Raja Ranjit Singh was adamant that no
लेकिन राजा रंजीत सिंह जी अड़ गए कि हमारी
army could just step on our land like that.  The
जमीन के ऊपर से ऐसे ही कोई आर्मी पैर रख
reserve of 42 million tonnes was
सकती। 42 मिलियन टन का जो रिजर्व था वो
found in Balochistan but
निकला बलचिस्तान में लेकिन उसके प्रॉफिट
China took away 50% of its profit and the Balochs
का 50% चाइना उठा के ले गया और बलोचों के
got only 2% of its profit.  There is only one Baloch community in the whole world
लगा। पूरी दुनिया के अंदर एक बलोच कौम ही
whose leaders
है जिनके लीडर्स अपने बच्चों के साथ आगे
come forward and fight along with their children.  Decisions are not taken sitting in expensive hotels.
आके लड़ते हैं। महंगे होटलों में बैठ के
Neither bow nor sell, just fight, not Sepak,
ना झुकदा ना बिकदा सिर्फ लड़ा सीपक नहीं
Baloch
बलोचोदा हक
want their rights, now see the people of Balochistan have been
चाहिएदा अब देखिए बलूचिस्तान के लोग अपने
raising their voice for their rights and identity.
राइट्स और आइडेंटिटी के लिए आवाज उठाते
But this voice does
रहे हैं। लेकिन ये जो आवाज है यह ग्लोबल
not reach the global level with clarity and impact.
लेवल पर क्लेरिटी और इंपैक्ट के साथ नहीं
Sometimes political noise, sometimes media
पहुंचती। कभी पॉलिटिकल नॉइज़ कभी मीडिया
silence and sometimes lack of framing does not allow this issue to
साइलेंस और कभी फ्रेमिंग की कमी इस इशू को
find a place in the world's narrative.
दुनिया के नैरेटिव में जगह नहीं बनाने
And this is not just about Balochistan, it is about every
देती। और ये सिर्फ बलूचिस्तान की नहीं हर
person who has something
उस इंसान की बात है जिसके पास कहने को कुछ
important to say but is stopped due to lack of tools.
इंपॉर्टेंट है पर टूल्स की कमी उसे रोकती
So AI is not just a tech revolution.  There is
है। इसलिए एआई सिर्फ एक टेक रिवॉल्यूशन
an equalizer that gives every person the
नहीं है। एक इक्वलाइजर है जो हर इंसान को
power to become skilled.
यह पावर देता है कि वो स्किल्ड बने। अपने
Give structure to your ideas and
आइडियाज को स्ट्रक्चर दें और उन्हें
present them impactfully to the world.  If
इंपैक्टफुली दुनिया के सामने रख सके। अगर
you want to grow your career by spending two days this weekend,
आप इस वीकेंड दो दिन देके करियर में ग्रोथ
I would recommend Outskill’s 2-day
चाहते हैं तो मैं आउटस्किल का दो दिन का
AI training program.
एआई ट्रेनिंग प्रोग्राम रेकमेंड करूंगा।
In which there will be 16 hours of live AI training
जिसमें 16 आवर्स की लाइव एआई ट्रेनिंग
on Saturday and Sunday.  11:00 am
होगी ऑन सैटरडे एंड संडे। 11:00 से शाम
to 7:00 pm.  Now this program costs ₹10,000.
7:00 बजे तक। अब ये प्रोग्राम तो ₹10,000
But it is 100% free for my viewers.  The
का है। पर मेरे व्यूअर्स के लिए 100% फ्री
link is in the description.  Outskill
है। लिंक डिस्क्रिप्शन में है। आउटस्किल
World is India’s first AI focused
वर्ल्ड इंडिया का पहला एआई फोकस
platform.  Back by Runaround AI
प्लेटफार्म है। बैक बाय रनाउंड एआई
Investors and Founders.  In this you
इन्वेस्टर्स एंड फाउंडर्स। इसमें आप
will learn 20 plus real world AI tools,
सीखोगे 20 प्लस रियल वर्ल्ड एI टूल्स,
form engineering, AI models, Excel,
प्र्प्ट इंजीनियरिंग, एआई मॉडल्स, एक्सेल,
presentation and analytics through AI.  and
प्रेजेंटेशन एंड एनालिटिक्स थ्रू एआई। और
building AI tools without coding.  Whether you
बिना कोडिंग के एआई टूल्स बनाना। चाहे आप
are a techie or non-techie, sales, marketing,
टेकी हो या नॉन टेक सेल्स, मार्केटिंग,
HR, finance, business or founder, it is
एचआर, फाइनेंस, बिजनेस या फाउंडर ये सबके
for everyone.  Already 1 lakh people have joined.
लिए है। ऑलरेडी 1 लाख लोग जुड़ चुके हैं।
You can also join.  The link
आप भी जुड़ सकते हैं। लिंक डिस्क्रिप्शन
is in the description.  Don’t miss the Friday 7:00pm onboarding
में है। फ्राइडे 7:00 pm का ऑनबोर्डिंग
call.  So let's come back to the topic.
कॉल मिस ना करें। तो टॉपिक पे वापस आते
See, Pakistan has
हैं। देखिए पाकिस्तान ने अपने टाइम पे
seen many big crises in its time.  Economy,
बड़ी-बड़ी क्राइसिस देखी। इकॉनमी,
military rule, political drama, everything.
मिलिट्री रूल, पॉलिटिकल ड्रामा सब कुछ।
But in the current time, the
लेकिन अभी ये जो टाइम चल रहा है इसमें
situation has become such that the question has now reached the
सिचुएशन ऐसी हो गई है कि बात अब पाकिस्तान
survival of Pakistan.  Right now,
के सर्वाइवल तक पे आ चुकी है। अभी आप कोई
pick up any newspaper and in Pakistan, the
भी न्यूज़पेपर उठाओ पाकिस्तान के अंदर ये
only
जो बलूचिस्तान वाली प्रॉब्लम है सिर्फ
discussion going on everywhere is about the problem of Balochistan.
इसके बारे में ही हर तरफ डिस्कशन हो रहा
And the way Balochistan is
है। और जिस तरह से बलूचिस्तान खुद की
creating its own army etc.
आर्मी वगैरह बना रहा है। अभी आने वाले
You will get to hear this name more in the times to come.   But
टाइम में आपको ये नाम और सुनने को मिलेगा।
now the question is what kind of
अब लेकिन क्वेश्चन यह है कि ऐसी क्या
problem arose within Pakistan that its
दिक्कत आ गई पाकिस्तान के अंदर कि ये जो
Balochistan province
पाकिस्तान का बलूचिस्तान प्रोवंस है ये
started talking about separating from Pakistan and forming its own country.  These people are attacking the Pakistan Army every day.
की बात करने लगा। आए दिन ये लोग पाकिस्तान
Just a few
आर्मी के ऊपर हमले कर रहे हैं। अभी थोड़े
days ago you might have seen that a train was
दिन पहले ही आपने देखा होगा कि एक ट्रेन
hijacked and people were ready to sacrifice their lives.
हक कर ली थी और अपनी जान तक देने को रेडी
But now
हो गए हैं कि हम जान दे देंगे। लेकिन अब
we cannot live with Pakistan.  We were
हम पाकिस्तान के साथ नहीं रह सकते। हमें
linked with deception.  Now we have to create our own
जो धोखे से जोड़ा गया। अब हमें वापस अपना
separate country Balochistan again.  Now look, the
अलग देश बलूचिस्तान बनाना है। अब देखिए
word Balochistan, even though it is
बलूचिस्तान ये जो वर्ड है भले ही ये
coming more in the news now, but this
न्यूज़ में अभी ज्यादा आ रहा है लेकिन ये
problem is a very old problem
जो प्रॉब्लम है ये प्रॉब्लम बहुत पुरानी
and many such things have happened in the past
है और पास्ट में कई ऐसी चीजें हुई हैं
due to which the problem has become so big today.
जिसकी वजह से दिक्कत आज इतनी बड़ी बन चुकी
And to understand this whole game, we will
है। और इस पूरे गेम को समझने के लिए हमें
have to go back a bit.  And before that let
थोड़ा पीछे जाना पड़ेगा। और उससे पहले एक
me tell you one thing.  See,
चीज मैं आपको बता देता हूं। देखिए ये जो
this Pakistan is mainly divided into four provinces.
पाकिस्तान है ये मेनली चार प्रोविंसेस में
This is Khyber Pakhtoon Khawa.   It
डिवाइडेड है। ये है खैबर पख्तून खावा।
shares its border with Afghanistan.  Then
इसका बॉर्डर अफगानिस्तान से लगता है। फिर
this is Punjab.  It has a border with India.
यह पंजाब है। इसका इंडिया के साथ बॉर्डर
This is the main province of Pakistan.
है। यह पाकिस्तान का मेन प्रोविंस है।
All the army generals you see come from here.
जितने भी आर्मी जनरल आप देखोगे सब यहीं से
And the
निकलते हैं। और सबसे ज्यादा रिसोर्सेज जो
province of Punjab enjoys the maximum resources.
हैं वो भी पंजाब प्रोविंस जो है वही एंजॉय
This here, this is Sindh.  It also
करता है। ये इधर ये है सिंध। इसका भी
shares its border with India.  And this is
बॉर्डर इंडिया से लगता है। और ये है
Balochistan which shares its border with Iran and
बलूचिस्तान जिसका बॉर्डर ईरान और
Afghanistan.  So see, this
अफगानिस्तान से लगता है। तो देखिए ये जो
area of ​​Balochistan, in the 12th century, there was
बलूचिस्तान वाला जो एरिया था 12्थ सेंचुरी
really no boundary etc.
में एज सच कोई बाउंड्री वगैरह नहीं थी इस
of this area and neither was this area named
एरिया की और ना ही इस एरिया का नाम कहीं
Balochistan anywhere.  In this map, you are
बलूचिस्तान था। यह जो इस मैप में आप पिंक
seeing the pink area, here
एरिया देख रहे हो, यहां पे अलग-अलग एरिया
small Baloch tribes used to live in different areas.  Like
में छोटी-छोटी बलूच ट्राइब रहती थी। जैसे
Makran Tribe, Kachi Tribe, Sistan
मकरान ट्राइब, कच्ची ट्राइब, सिस्टान
Tribe, Turbat Tribe.  There was
ट्राइब, टर्बट ट्राइब। यहां कोई पॉलिटिकल
no political system here.  Every tribe had its own
सिस्टम नहीं था। बस हर ट्राइब का अपना एक
chieftain.  And like this different
सरदार होता था। और ऐसे ही अलग-अलग
tribes were living in this area.  And if
ट्राइब्स इस एरिया में रह रही थी। और अगर
you look at this map carefully, then at
आप इस मैप को ध्यान से देखोगे, तो आज का
that
बॉर्डर है, उसके पास वाले एरिया में भी उस
time these tribes had occupied small pieces of land
टाइम पे ये ट्राइब्स थोड़ी-थोड़ी जगह
and were living in the areas near the border of today's Iran and Afghanistan.
इन्होंने ले रखी थी और वहां पे रह रही थी।
Because at that time the border was
क्योंकि उस टाइम पे बॉर्डर क्लियरली
not clearly decided.  Now what happens is that when these
डिसाइड नहीं था। अब होता क्या है कि जब ये
tribes were living in this area,
ट्राइब्स इस एरिया में रह रही थी तो इनके
a man named Mir Jalal Khan was
बीच में एक मीर जलाल खान नाम का एक आदमी
very famous among them.  So at this particular time
बहुत फेमस था। तो इसी पर्टिकुलर टाइम पे
Mir Jalal said that look, it is
मीर जलाल ने कहा कि देखिए हम अलग-अलग जो
better for us to
रह रहे हैं उससे बेटर है कि हम साथ में
live together rather than living separately, so that if any trouble arises, we will be
मिलकर रहें जिससे अगर कोई मुसीबत आए तो हम
united and will be able to help each other.
एकजुट हो के रहेंगे और एक दूसरे की मदद कर
So what did Mir Jalal do?  I
पाएंगे। तो मीर जलाल ने क्या किया? इस
went and talked to 44 tribes in this area, brought them
एरिया में 44 ट्राइब से जाकर बात की और
all together and formed an alliance.  This
सबको इकट्ठा करके एक अलायंस बनाया। ये
was the first time these tribes united within this area.
पहली बार था जब इस एरिया के अंदर ये
They did not create a new country but rather created a model
नहीं बनाई थी इन्होंने बल्कि एक मॉडल सा
in which everything was going on like before.  The
बना लिया था जिसमें सब कुछ पहले की तरह ही
chieftains were managing their tribes in the same way as they used to do earlier.  The
चल रहा था। सरदार जैसे पहले अपनी-अपनी
only difference was that 44 tribes had
थे। बस फर्क इतना था कि 44 ट्राइब्स ने एक
decided to unite by forming an alliance
अलायंस बनाकर एकजुट होने का डिसीजन कर
which was being led by Mir Jalal.
लिया था जिसको मीर जलाल जो है वो लीड कर
And the decision to form this alliance, the
रहे थे। और यही जो अलायंस बनाने वाला जो
foundation for creating Balochistan was laid at this time.
बनाने की जो नीव थी इसी टाइम पर रख दी गई
That is why you will see that even today people
थी। इसलिए आप देखोगे आज की डेट में भी लोग
consider Mir Jalal Khan as the founding father of the
मीर जलाल खान को फाउंडिंग फादर मानते हैं
Baloch community.  You
बलूच कम्युनिटी का। इनकी इंपोर्टेंस आप
can understand their importance from the children of Mir Jalal Khan
इससे समझ सकते हो कि मीर जलाल खान के जो
like Rind, Lashari, Koraie, Bibi
बच्चे थे जैसे रिंड, लशारी, कोराए, बीबी
Jato.  Today, there are many
जाटो। आज की डेट में बलूचिस्तान में कई
such areas in Balochistan which are named after their children.
ऐसे एरिया हैं इनके बच्चों के नाम से पड़े
Like Rindabad Village, Kurai Village,
हैं। जैसे रिंदाबाद विलेज, कुराई विलेज,
Jatoi City.  All these are derived from the names of his children.
जटोई सिटी। ये सब इनके बच्चों के नाम से
Now see,
ही डिराइव हुए हैं। अब देखिए काफी टाइम तक
this model which was made, has been working for a long time.
ये जो मॉडल बनाया गया था ये चलता है। इसके
After this, by the time the 15th century came, after Mir Jalal,
बाद 15थ सेंचुरी आते-आते मीर जलाल के बाद
Mir Chakar Rin also came.
मीर चकर रिन जो थे ये भी
He did the same thing and organised it further
आए। इन्होंने भी सेम चीज की इसको और
and kept all the tribes united.
ऑर्गेनाइज किया और सारी ट्राइब्स को एकजुट
And at that time, in this area, people were
रखा। और उस टाइम पे ये जो एरिया था ये जो
living in semi-organised structures.
सेमी ऑर्गेनाइज्ड स्ट्रक्चर में रह रहे
At that time
थे। उस टाइम पे बलूचिस्तान नहीं बल्कि रिन
people knew this area not as Balochistan but by the name of Rin Lashari Union.
लशारी यूनियन नाम से लोग जानते थे इस
Now what happens is that this tribe was
एरिया को। अब होता क्या है कि ये ट्राइब
living together.  But when the year 1666
मिलजुल के तो रह रही थी। लेकिन ईयर 1666
came, the Safavid Empire was
जब आया तो इधर ईरान में सफाविद अंपायर
becoming very big in Iran.  If you look on the other side,
बहुत बड़ा बनता जा रहा था। वहीं दूसरी तरफ
you had a Mughal umpire.  So because
देखोगे तो आप मुगल अंपायर था। तो क्योंकि
these two big umpires were
ये दोनों बड़े-बड़े अंपायर जो थे वो
next to each other.  Due to this, the Baloch tribes
अगल-बगल ही थे। तो इससे जो बलूच ट्राइब्स
who were living here were under
थी जो बीच में यहां रह रही थी उनके ऊपर
a lot of pressure from time to time.
टाइम टू टाइम बहुत ज्यादा प्रेशर रहता था।
So because of all the pressure that was developing on them,
तो यह सारा जो प्रेशर इन पर डेवलप हो रहा
they felt that they needed to
था इसको लेके इनको लगा कि इनको अपने आप को
create a system to protect themselves.
प्रोटेक्ट करने के लिए एक सिस्टम बनाने की
He
जरूरत है। इन्होंने अपने आसपास के
observed the empires around him to see how they were working.  Getting
एंपायर्स को देखा कि वो कैसे काम कर रहे
inspired from him, I also
हैं। उन्हीं से इंस्पायर हो के खुद भी एक
started creating a central authority.  Just like
सेंट्रल अथॉरिटी बनाना स्टार्ट किया। जैसे
the rest of the empires were working.
बाकी एंपायर्स काम कर रहे थे। कुछ उसी से
Started building a structure similar to that.
मिलताजुलता स्ट्रक्चर बनाने का स्टार्ट
So all these tribes were
किया। तो ये जो सारी ट्राइब्स इस एरिया
living in this area.  Among all these tribes, there was
में रह रही थी। इन्हीं सारी ट्राइब्स के
another tribe whose name was
बीच में एक और ट्राइब थी जिसका नाम था
Ahmed Jai Brah Tribe.  In this map, the
अहमद जाई ब्राह ट्राइब। ये मैप में ये जो
area which you are seeing by the name Kalat,
आप कलात नाम से ये जो एरिया देख रहे हो
this tribe was in this area.  And there was
इसी एरिया में ये ट्राइब थी। और इस ट्राइब
a man in this tribe named Mir Ahmed Khan.  So when the
के अंदर एक आदमी था मीर अहमद खान। तो जब
talk of forming a central authority was going on,
सेंट्रल अथॉरिटी बनाने की बात चल रही थी
all the tribes together made Mir Ahmed Khan the
तो सारी ट्राइब्स ने मिलके मीर अहमद खान
Khan of Kalad.  Now what is this Khan of
को खान ऑफ कलाद बना दिया। अब ये खान ऑफ
Kalad?  Like the king is the head of the state.  In the
कलाद क्या है? जैसे बादशाह हेड ऑफ द स्टेट
same way they
होता है। ठीक उसी तरीके से इन्होंने उसको
named him Khan of Kalad, meaning he will lead.
नाम दिया खान ऑफ कलाद कि मतलब यही लीड
Now see, one thing is worth keeping in mind here
करेंगे। अब देखिए यहां पे एक चीज ये ध्यान
that all these tribes had
रखने वाली है कि ये जो सारी ट्राइब्स थी
made Mir Ahmed Khan the Khan of Kalat.
इन्होंने खान ऑफ कलात तो बना दिया था मीर
But the chieftains of some tribes
अहमद खान को। लेकिन कुछ ट्राइब्स जो थी
said that we are
उनके जो सरदार थे उन्होंने कहा कि हम खान
accepting you as the Khan of Kalat but we will manage our
ऑफ कलात मान तो रहे हैं आपको लेकिन हमारी
tribe's and our area
जो ट्राइब है हमारा जो एरिया है वहां उसको
ourselves. So because of this, the
हम खुद मैनेज करेंगेI तो इस वजह से ये जो
dark green area that you can see in the map was being directly
मैप में आप ये डार्क ग्रीन एरिया देख रहे
ruled by the Khan of Kalat i.e. Mir Ahmed and the light
डायरेक्टली रूल कर रहे थे और जो लाइट
green area was
ग्रीन एरिया है इसको खान ऑफ कलात ने
indirectly ruled by the Khan of Kalat and this entire
इनडायरेक्टली रूल किया और यह जो पूरा
green area, whether it is light green or
ग्रीन एरिया चाहे वो लाइट ग्रीन है या फिर
dark green, was called the
डार्क ग्रीन है इस पूरे एरिया को कहा गया
Khanate of Kalat.
खानेत ऑफ कलात
Later on, this Khanate of Kalat would
आगे चलके यही खानेत ऑफ कलात बलूचिस्तान
become Balochistan.  So whenever there is talk of Kalat State or Khanate of
बनेगा। तो जब भी कलात स्टेट या खानेत ऑफ
Kalat, then you should understand that this entire
कलात की बात हो तो आप समझ जाना कि इस पूरे
light and dark green area is being
जो लाइट और डार्क ग्रीन ये जो एरिया है
talked about.  So when this Khanate
पूरा इसकी बात हो रही है। तो जब ये खानेत
of Kalat became a proper system, then the
ऑफ कलात एक प्रॉपर सिस्टम बना तो लॉ ट्रेड
entire setup of law, trade, military was made and then
मिलिट्री ये सारा सेटअप बनाया गया और फिर
this system continued for a long time and then
काफी टाइम तक ये सिस्टम चला और फिर
gradually when the year 1749 came and
धीरे-धीरे करके जब ईयर 1749 आया और मीर
after Mir Ahmed Khan, his grandson Mir Nasir Khan
अहमद खान के बाद इनके पोते मीर नासिर खान
became the Khan of Kalat.  The Baloch
ये बनते हैं खान ऑफ़ कला। बलोच जो हैं वो
consider this time as the golden period.   As
इस टाइम को गोल्डन पीरियड मानते हैं।
soon as Nasir Khan came, he
नासिर खान ने आते ही इस पूरे खानेत ऑफ
created a good political system in the entire Khanate of Kalat.
कलात में एक अच्छा पॉलिटिकल सिस्टम बनाया।
He set up the Baloch Army which included
इन्होंने बलोच आर्मी सेटअप की जिसमें
25,000 soldiers.  Kept 1000 camels
25,000 सोल्जर्स बनाए। 1000 कैमल रखे
in it.  Look, remember this thing, I will
उसमें। देखिए इसमें ये चीज याद रखिएगा मैं
also repeat it that there were
रिपीट भी कर देता हूं कि खानेत ऑफ कलात
many tribes in the Khanate of Kalat.  Who had their own separate
में कई ट्राइब्स थी। जिनके खुद के अलग
systems.  Their chiefs used to
सिस्टम थे। उनके जो सरदार थे वो उनको
control them.  But all this was going on under the Khan of
चलाते थे। लेकिन ये सब चलते थे खान ऑफ
Kalat.  So what did the Khan of Kalat
कलात के अंडर। तो इसीलिए खान ऑफ कलात ने
do?  The
क्या किया था? इस एरिया की जितनी भी बलूच
chiefs of all the Baloch tribes of this area were called and a
ट्राइब थी सबके जो सरदार थे इनको बुला के
council system was created so that if any decision was to be taken,
काउंसिल सिस्टम बनाया था ताकि कोई फैसला
everyone could agree on it.  This
हो तो सबकी सहमति हो सके। सब कुछ यही
council used to decide everything.  The Council worked in the
काउंसिल डिसाइड करती थी। जैसे
same manner as the Parliament works.
पार्लियामेंट काम करती है ठीक उसी तरीके
Now after this comes the year
से काउंसिल काम करती थी। अब इसके बाद ईयर
1830 and with the arrival of this year the real
आता है 1830 और ये ईयर आते-आते असली
problems started.  By this
दिक्कतें स्टार्ट होना शुरू होती हैं। इस
time the British had arrived.  He was
टाइम पे ब्रिटिशर्स आ चुके थे। अपना
ruling over his undivided India.
अनडिवाइडेड इंडिया पे रूल कर रहे थे।
But at the same time, there was
लेकिन सेम टाइम पे क्या था कि ब्रिटिशर्स
a
और रशिया जो थे इनके बीच में एक
geopolitical battle going on between the British and Russia, which was
जियोपॉलिटिकल लड़ाई चल रही थी जिसे द
also called The Great Game.
ग्रेट गेम भी बोला जाता
So this area of ​​Central Asia which you are
है। तो ये जो सेंट्रल एशिया का एरिया आप
seeing, which includes Kazakhstan,
देख रहे हो जिसमें कजाकिस्तान,
Uzbekistan, Turkmenistan, this entire
उज्बेकिस्तान, तर्कमेनिस्तान ये पूरा
Central Asia was considered a very important area.
सेंट्रल एशिया बहुत ही इंपॉर्टेंट एरिया
All the important trade routes,
माना जाता था। सारे इंपॉर्टेंट ट्रेड रूट,
silk route, economic activities, everything happened
सिल्क रूट, इकोनॉमिक एक्टिविटी सब कुछ
from here.  And if there was presence
यहीं से होती थी। और इस सेंट्रल एशिया के
of any empire and military in this Central Asia, then
अंदर किसी भी एंपायर और मिलिट्री की
it would have provided a huge strategic advantage.  So
स्ट्रेटेजिक एडवांटेज मिलता था इससे। तो
what Russia did was that it gradually
रशिया ने क्या किया कि धीरे-धीरे करके
expanded its empire by occupying Kazakhstan, Uzbekistan in Central Asia.  And
एंपायर था उसको एक्सपेंड कर लिया था। और
along with this, they were also moving towards Afghanistan.
इसके साथ-साथ वो अफगानिस्तान की तरफ भी
For this, he also sent
बढ़ रहे थे। इसके लिए इन्होंने ईयर 1837
his diplomat Captain Ivan to Afghanistan in the year 1837.  My
में अफगानिस्तान के अंदर अपने डिप्लोमेट
friend Mohammad Khan, who was the ruler of Afghanistan at that time, had
के जो रूलर थे उस टाइम के दोस्त मोहम्मद
started talking to him.  Now, when it was
खान इनसे बात स्टार्ट कर दी थी। अब जब
entering Russia or Afghanistan, the
रशिया या अफगानिस्तान में घुस रहा था तो
British who were
यहां से ब्रिटिशर्स जो थे जो इंडिया के
sitting on India got worried.   The
ऊपर बैठे हुए थे वो परेशान हो गए।
British who were ruling India
ब्रिटिशर्स जो इंडिया के ऊपर रूल कर रहे
considered India to be a very important part of their country because there were a
पार्ट मानते थे क्योंकि यहां पे बहुत
lot of resources here and the way Russia was
ज्यादा रिसोर्सेज थी और रशिया जिस तरीके
growing and then slowly it was
से बढ़ रहा था और फिर धीरे-धीरे
entering into Afghanistan as well.  There was a strong
अफगानिस्तान में भी घुस रहा था। बहुत
possibility that it would reach the border of India
पॉसिबिलिटी थी कि वो इंडिया के बॉर्डर तक
and the British and Russia did
पहुंच जाता और ब्रिटिशर्स और रशिया आपस
not want to fight among themselves.  So now from here the
में लड़ना नहीं चाहते थे। तो अब यहां से
Britishers started using their brains.
ब्रिटिशर्स ने अपना दिमाग लगाना चालू
He wondered if there should be
किया। उन्होंने यह सोचा कि अगर इंडिया और
a buffer zone between India and Russia.
रशिया के बीच में एक बफर ज़ोन होना चाहिए।
If this does not happen then a big problem will arise.
अगर यह नहीं हुआ तो बहुत बड़ी दिक्कत खड़ी
And whichever country is in this buffer zone should act
हो जाएगी। और जो भी कंट्री इस बफर ज़ोन में
according to our wishes.  And if this is
हो वो हमारे हिसाब से चले। और अगर ये चीज
done then Russia will not be able to reach India.
कर ली तो रशिया इंडिया तक पहुंच ही नहीं
So for this the British had
पाएगा। तो इसके लिए ब्रिटिशर्स ने प्लान
made a plan that
ये बनाया था कि अफगानिस्तान पे रशिया से
we will attack Afghanistan before Russia and
पहले पहुंच के हम लोग हमला कर देंगे और
remove the ruler of Afghanistan, Dost Mohammad Khan and make our puppet ruler
खान इसको हटा के और अपना जो पपेट रूलर है
Shah Shuja the ruler of Afghanistan.  This would result in the
शाह सूजा इसको अफगानिस्तान का रूलर बना
British having more control over Afghanistan than Russia.
ऊपर रशिया से ज्यादा ब्रिटिशर्स का
He had influence.  Now
कंट्रोल रहे। उनका इन्फ्लुएंस रहे। अब
if they wanted to attack Afghanistan and
अफगानिस्तान पे अगर हमला करना है और अपना
install their ruler there then the British would have to
रूलर बैठाना है तो इंडिया से ब्रिटिशर्स
send their army from India to Afghanistan
को अपनी आर्मी अफगानिस्तान में पहुंचानी
and for that they would need a route.  So
पड़ेगी और उसके लिए एक रूट चाहिए होगा। तो
one route from here was the Northern Route through Peshawar and
एक रूट तो ये इधर से नॉर्दन रूट पेशावर और
Khyber pass.  But there
खाइबर के पास के थ्रू जाता था। लेकिन सिख
was a Sikh umpire at that time.  So when the British were
अंपायर था उस टाइम। तो जब ब्रिटिशर्स इस
asking to withdraw their army from this area, then
एरिया से अपनी आर्मी ले जाने को कह रहे थे
Raja Ranjit Singh ji was the Sikh emperor.
तो सिख अंपायर के जो राजा रंजीत सिंह जी
He clearly refused, saying that the
थे। उन्होंने साफ मना कर दिया कि जो
British Army will
ब्रिटिश आर्मी है वो हमारी धरती से ऐसे
not make such a path through our land.  So when the
रास्ता बना के नहीं जाएगी। तो जब सिख
option of the Sikh umpire did not seem right for the
अंपायर वाला ऑप्शन सही नहीं पड़ा
British, then their eyes
ब्रिटिशर्स के लिए तो यहां से इनकी नजर
fell on the Khaniyat of Kalat which was
पड़ती है खानियत ऑफ कलात जिसको कलात स्टेट
also known as the Kalat State, at that time some people of the
भी बोलते थे उस टाइम पे कुछ लोग तो
British made a plan that they will reach Afghanistan
ब्रिटिशर्स ने प्लान बनाया कि वो इंडिया
from India via Bolan Pass, Kota Chaman
से बोलन पास कोटा चमन ऐसे करके
and in between, this
पहुंचेंगे और बीच में ये जो बोलन पास कोटा
area of ​​Balochistan around Bolan Pass, Kota Chaman,
चमन वाला जो बलूचिस्तान का जो एरिया है
I am calling it Balochistan now, at that time was
मैं बलूचिस्तान अभी बोल रहा हूं उस समय
not the Balochistan area.
बलूचिस्तान एरिया नहीं पड़ा था ये जो
What did the British do for this area, they
एरिया था इसके लिए अंग्रेजों ने क्या किया
sent their diplomat Alexander Bernies to the then Khan of Kalat Mehrab Khan so that after taking permission etc. and agreement
भेजा ताकि यह परमिशन वगैरह लेके एग्रीमेंट
etc., they could make arrangements to leave from here.
वगैरह लेके यहां से निकलने का अरेंजमेंट
Basically the British were very
करें। बेसिकली ब्रिटिशर्स जो थे वो बहुत
powerful.  He had to leave this area.  So
पावरफुल थे। उनको इस एरिया से जाना था। तो
he wanted proper control over this area.
इस एरिया पे वो प्रॉपर कंट्रोल चाहते थे।
So for this he first made a deal with the Khan of Kalat.  We
तो इसके लिए इन्होंने पहले खान ऑफ कलात से
told them that we will
एक डील करी। उनसे कहा कि हम आपको
support you financially and you let us
फाइनेंसियल सपोर्ट करेंगे और आप हमें इस
use this area.  Now the Khan of Kalat was
एरिया को यूज़ करने दो। अब खान ऑफ़ कलात की
also helpless.  He accepted this deal.  Now
भी मजबूरी थी। उन्होंने ये डील मान ली। अब
after this, the year 1839 was the time when the
इसके बाद ईयर 1839 ये वो टाइम आया जब
British had to use the Kalat State area to
ब्रिटिशर्स को कलात स्टेट इस एरिया को यूज
transport their army to Afghanistan for
करके अपनी आर्मी को अफगानिस्तान पहुंचाना
attack.  Now even though the
था अटैक करने के लिए। अब भले ही
British had signed an agreement with the Khan of Kalat
ब्रिटिशर्स ने खान ऑफ कलात से एग्रीमेंट
that they would leave this area.
साइन कर लिया था कि वो इस एरिया से
But the local people of this area were
जाएंगे। लेकिन लोकल लोग जो थे इस एरिया के
not happy with this thing even though they had signed with Khan of Kala.  He said
वो इस चीज से खुश नहीं थे। उन्होंने कहा
that since it is our land, we will not let it go like this.
कि हमारी जमीन है तो हम ऐसे नहीं जाने
So, going against the agreement made by Khan of Kalat, they launched
देंगे। तो उन्होंने खान ऑफ कलात ने जो
small attacks on the British Army.
ब्रिटिश आर्मी पे छोटे-छोटे अटैक कर दिए।
Now when these attacks happened, the British felt
अब जब ये अटैक हुए तो ब्रिटिशर्स को लगा
that this Mehrab Khan was
कि ये जो मेहराब खान है यह तो अपने लोगों
not able to stop his people from attacking.
को अटैक करने से रोक ही नहीं पा रहा है।
And he also had a doubt that
और साथ में इनको यह भी डाउट हुआ कि क्या
maybe Mehrab Khan is not stopping him intentionally.
पता मेहराब खान जानबूझ के ना रोक रहा हो।
He may want such attacks to continue.
वो चाह रहा हो कि ऐसे ही अटैक होते रहे।
Along with this, there was also a doubt on Mehrab Khan
इसके साथ-साथ एक डाउट ये भी था मेहराब खान
that perhaps he had some links with Afghanistan too.
के ऊपर कि शायद यह अफगानिस्तान से भी इसके
So overall the British
कुछ लिंक हैं। तो कुल मिला के ब्रिटिशर्स
felt that even though Mehrab Khan had
को यह लग रहा था कि भले ही मेहराब खान ने
signed the agreement.  But there is a
एग्रीमेंट साइन कर दिया हो। लेकिन यह
possibility that he himself is getting attacked from behind.
पॉसिबिलिटी है कि पीछे से यह खुद ही अटैक
So the British, in anger,
करवा रहा हो। तो ब्रिटिशर्स ने गुस्से में
attacked the Kalat State in November 1839
नवंबर 1839 में कलात स्टेट इस पे अटैक
and killed Mehrab Khan. Mehrab
करके मेहराब खान को मार दिया और जो मेहराब
Khan's opponent, Shahnawaz Khan, was made the Khan of
खान का एंटी था शाहनवाज खान उसको खान ऑफ़
Kalat, who worked according to the British.
कलात बना दिया जो ब्रिटिशर्स के हिसाब से
Now after this the British
चलता था। अब इसके बाद ब्रिटिशर्स को यह
understood that if they wanted to protect this entire area
समझ में आ गया था कि अगर इस पूरे एरिया को
from Russia and create a buffer zone, then
रशिया से बचा के बफर ज़ोन बनाना है तो कलात
this region of Kalat State would have to be kept under their control.  The
स्टेट के इस रीजन को अपने कंट्रोल में
British were not interested in
रखना होगा। ब्रिटिशर जो थे पूरे कलात
taking over the entire Kalat State
स्टेट को अपने अंडर में लेने के लिए
because at that time there was
इंटरेस्टेड नहीं थे क्योंकि उस टाइम पे
vacant land far and wide.  There were
दूर-दूर तक खाली लैंड थे। रिसोर्सेज इतने
not that many resources and to take over any land one had to
थे नहीं और किसी भी लैंड को अपने अंडर में
deploy a lot of army etc.
लेने में बहुत सारी आर्मी वगैरह लगानी
So he was not interested in this thing.
पड़ती है। तो वो इस चीज में इंटरेस्टेड
So what did they do?  The Kalat
नहीं थे। तो उन्होंने क्या किया? कलात
State was divided into two parts.
स्टेट जो था इसको दो पार्ट में डिवाइड कर
One part was this region, the Pink
दिया। एक पार्ट ये रीजन था पिंक वाला
area of ​​Quetta, Bolan Pass, Chaman, Chagai.
क्वेटा बोलन पास, चमन, चगई ये वाला एरिया।
This area was directly
ये एरिया जो था ब्रिटिशर्स ने डायरेक्टली
controlled by the British with the help of their military.  And the
कंट्रोल किया अपनी मिलिट्री के दम पे। और
rest of the area was controlled indirectly.  He
बाकी जो एरिया था ये इनडायरेक्टली कंट्रोल
placed a ruler there who would run things according to his wishes and
वहां पे बैठा दिया और टाइम टू टाइम
gave financial support from time to time so that the inside
फाइनेंसियल सपोर्ट दिया ताकि अंदर का जो
area also remained under control.  But the
एरिया है वो भी कंट्रोल में रहे। लेकिन
British never colonised the Kalat State the way they had colonised India.  So the
ब्रिटिशर्स ने कभी भी नहीं किया था। तो
British created their influence in Afghanistan by attacking and
ब्रिटिशर्स ने अफगानिस्तान पे भी हमले
negotiating and using different tactics,
करके बातचीत करके अलग-अलग टैक्टिक्स यूज़
and in a
करके वहां पे अपना इन्फ्लुएंस बनाया और
similar way they increased their influence in Iran.  The
ईरान में भी ऐसे ही अपना इन्फ्लुएंस
British who
बढ़ाया। अंग्रेज जो रशिया और इंडिया के
wanted to create a buffer zone between Russia and India, did
बीच में एक बफर ज़ोन बनाना चाह रहे थे वो
it very easily. And
बहुत ही आसानी से इन्होंने बना लिया और ये
while creating this buffer zone, they
जो बफर ज़ोन ये लोग बना रहे थे इसके चक्कर
also started marking the borders of Kalat State,
में कलात स्टेट के बॉर्डर की भी मार्किंग
meaning they started officially registering the borders
स्टार्ट कर दी थी मतलब ऑफिशियली बॉर्डर
because earlier there were no real borders, there were
क्योंकि पहले एज सच कोई बॉर्डर नहीं होते
frontiers, there used to be
थे फ्रंटियर्स होते थे दूर-दूर तक ऐसी
empty areas far and wide. So when the British
खाली एरिया पड़ा रहता था तो जब ब्रिटिशर्स
started creating the borders of Kalat State, a
ने कलात स्टेट के बॉर्डर बनाना चालू किए
large area near the borders of Kalat State
तो कलात स्टेट के बॉर्डर के पास का काफी
which touched the borders of Iran and Afghanistan was given to Iran and Afghanistan
एरिया जो ईरान और अफगानिस्तान के बॉर्डर
through the Gold Mines Line Agreement and sometimes through the Treaty of
एग्रीमेंट के थ्रू और कभी ट्रीटी ऑफ़
Gandamark,
गंडामार्क करके ईरान और अफगानिस्तान को दे
so that Iran and Afghanistan remain happy and
दिया ताकि ईरान और अफगानिस्तान खुश रह और
stay away from the influence of Russia. And
रशिया के इन्फ्लुएंस से दूर रहे और ये
a few days after doing all this, they also signed
सारी चीजें करने के थोड़े ही दिन बाद एथ
an official treaty with Kalat State on the 8th of December 1876 so
ऑफ दिसंबर 1876 में कलात स्टेट के साथ एक
that everything
ऑफिशियल ट्रीटी भी कर ली कि हर चीज ऑन
remains on paper, which is called the Treaty of Kalat.
पेपर भी रहे जिसको ट्रीटी ऑफ़ कलात कहते
These are some of his terms.  Article three of this treaty is
हैं। ये उसकी कुछ टर्म्स है। इस ट्रीटी का
very important.
जो आर्टिकल थ्री है वो बहुत इंपॉर्टेंट
Now it will be revealed what the meaning of this article is.
है। अभी आगे आएगा कि इस आर्टिकल की
Now after this, the
क्याेंस है। अब इसके बाद कलात स्टेट की
British took the foreign policy etc. of the Kalat State under their
फॉरेन पॉलिसी वगैरह ब्रिटिशर्स ने अपने
control and the internal matters on daily basis were given
अंडर में ली थी और जो डेली बेसिस के
to the Khan of Kalad and told him to
इंटरनल मैटर थे वो खान ऑफ कलाद को दे दिए
handle the internal matters himself.
थे कि इंटरनल मैटर तुम खुद संभालो और
After taking over the foreign policy, Russia
फॉरेन पॉलिसी लेने के बाद रशिया का इस
lost complete control over this area. In
एरिया से पूरा कंट्रोल चला गया और इसके
return, the British
बदले जो ब्रिटिशर्स थे उन्होंने कलाद
initially gave ₹000 per year to the Kalat State and then
स्टेट को शुरू में ₹00 दिए साल के और फिर
increased it to ₹1 lakh.  Now look,
इसको बढ़ा के ₹1 लाख कर दिए थे। अब देखिए
look at the map once again from here.   The
यहां से एक बार फिर से मैप देख लीजिए।
British retained the pink area using their military power.
पिंक एरिया ब्रिटिशर्स ने मिलिट्री के दम
This green area was
पे अपने पास रखा था। यह ग्रीन एरिया में
given to the Khan of Kalat to indirectly rule.  And then after this, in the year 1887, this
दिया था। और फिर इसके बाद ईयर 1887 में ये
pink area which was under the control of the British was
जो पिंक एरिया था जो ब्रिटिशर्स के
also
कंट्रोल में था इसको भी ऑन पेपर अपने अंडर
indirectly taken under British control on paper.  And when it was
इनडायरेक्टली ले लिया। और लीज़ के थ्रू जब
put on paper through lease, it was named
ऑन पेपर कराया गया तो इसका नाम रखा गया
British
ब्रिटिश
Balochistan.  And in this way the
बलूचिस्तान। और इस तरीके से ऑफिशियली पहली
name Balochistan was used officially for the first time.  The remaining
बार बलूचिस्तान का नाम यूज़ हुआ। बाकी बचा
Given Area was still
हुआ जो गिविन एरिया था वो अभी भी उसको
known as Kalat State.  Khanate of Art.  Now
कलात स्टेट ही बोलते थे। खानेत ऑफ कला। अब
see, for the next 50-60 years, no
देखिए इसके अगले 50-60 साल तक एज सच कोई
major event took place and then the
बड़ा इवेंट नहीं होता है और फिर
time for the British to leave came near,
ब्रिटिशर्स के जाने का टाइम पास आ जाता है
undivided India had to be divided and
जो अनडिवाइडेड इंडिया था उसका बंटवारा
Pakistan was to be formed, so at the same time, the
होना था पाकिस्तान बनना था तो सेम टाइम पे
Khan of Kalat, Mir Ahmed Yar Khan,
जो खान ऑफ कलात थे मीर अहमद यार खान
thought that now that the British are leaving,
इन्होने ये सोचा था कि अब जब अंग्रेज जा
we were not colonized by the British, so
रहे हैं तो हमें ब्रिटिशर्स ने कॉलोनाइज
we will now
तो किया नहीं था तो हम तो अब एक
become an independent country.
इंडिपेंडेंट कंट्री बन जाएंगे। इस चीज को
Khan of Kalat was
लेके खान ऑफ कलात जो थे वो इसलिए भी
confident about this matter because it was legally
कॉन्फिडेंट थे क्योंकि लीगली भी ये चीज
valid also.  First of all, according to Article 3 of the official treaty that was signed between the British and the Kalat State in the year 1876, the
वैलिड थी। सबसे पहली चीज ईयर 1876 में जो
British had
के हिसाब से ब्रिटिशर्स ने ऑन पेपर ये चीज
officially accepted on paper that the Kalat State is
ऑफिशियली एक्सेप्ट की थी कि कलात स्टेट
not a British area but an
ब्रिटिशर्स का एरिया नहीं है बल्कि एक
independent state and the area that the
इंडिपेंडेंट स्टेट है और जो एरिया
British had taken, which they
ब्रिटिशर्स ने लिया है जिसे ये ब्रिटिश
call British Balochistan, was also
बलूचिस्तान बोलते हैं वो भी एक एग्रीमेंट
taken under an agreement and lease.  That means like someone
और लीज़ के तहत लिया था। यानी कि जैसे कोई
lives on rent.  Along with this, in the year 1886, the
किराए पे रहता है। इसके साथ-साथ ईयर 1886
British Administration
में ब्रिटिश एडमिनिस्ट्रेशन ने अपनी
officially mentioned in its official report that
ऑफिशियल रिपोर्ट में ऑफिशियली ये चीज
Khan of Kalad was an
मेंशन की थी खान ऑफ कलाद को एक
independent ruler who was
इंडिपेंडेंट रूलर जो कि एक ट्रीटी के थ्रू
connected with the British through a treaty.  This thing
ब्रिटिशर्स के साथ कनेक्टेड है। ये चीज
was from the mansion.  And in the year 1877,
मेंशन की थी। और ईयर 1877 में दिल्ली
Khan of Kalat Khudadad Khan was summoned in the Delhi Imperial Assembly
इंपीरियल असेंबली में खान ऑफ कलात खुदादाद
as an independent king.
खान को एक इंडिपेंडेंट राजा की तरह बुलाया
Meaning that the British themselves believed that
था। मतलब कि ब्रिटिशर्स खुद मानते थे कि
Kalat State was an independent state.  So
कलात स्टेट एक इंडिपेंडेंट स्टेट है। तो
legally the British
लीगली ब्रिटिशर्स किसी भी स्टेज पे ये
could not say at any stage that the Kalat State was a
नहीं कह सकते थे कि कलात स्टेट जो है वो
part of the British Empire.  And if
ब्रिटिशर्स के एंपायर का पार्ट है। और अगर
the British had said this,
ऐसा कहते ब्रिटिशर्स तो इंटरनेशनलली भी
they would have faced a lot of problems internationally too.  But on the other
बहुत दिक्कतें होती उनको। लेकिन अगर दूसरी
hand, if Kalat State had become an independent country, then the
तरफ कलात स्टेट अगर एक इंडिपेंडेंट कंट्री
British as well as the
की तरह हो जाता तो ब्रिटिशर्स के साथ-साथ
US feared that Kalat State was very weak.  It may
यूएस को भी डर था कि कलात स्टेट काफी वीक
happen that Russia's
है। कहीं ये ना हो जाए कि रशिया का
influence increases again in this area.
इन्फ्लुएंस फिर से बढ़ जाए इस एरिया में।
And this area was very
और ये जो एरिया था स्ट्रेटेजिकली बहुत
important strategically.  And if this Kalat
ज्यादा इंपॉर्टेंट था। और अगर यही कलात
State joins with Pakistan, then the
स्टेट पाकिस्तान के साथ मिल जाता है तो
whole area becomes strong and Russia's
पूरा एरिया स्ट्रांग होता है और रशिया का
influence cannot increase.  Because the
इन्फ्लुएंस नहीं बढ़ पाता। क्योंकि
British had a very
पाकिस्तान के ऊपर ब्रिटिशर्स का काफी
good influence on Pakistan.  So, it was
अच्छा इन्फ्लुएंस था। तो ब्रिटिशर्स के
very important for the British that if the Kalat
लिए ये चीज बहुत इंपॉर्टेंट थी कि जो कलात
State joins Pakistan instead of becoming independent,
स्टेट है वो इंडिपेंडेंट होने की बजाय
it would be more in their
पाकिस्तान के साथ मिले तो वो चीज ज्यादा
favour.  So now from here
फेवर करेगी। तो अब यहां से इस एक
a game begins to deal with this complex situation in which the
कॉम्प्लेक्स सिचुएशन से निपटने के लिए एक
Khan of Art gets
गेम स्टार्ट होता है जिसमें खान ऑफ़ कला जो
trapped.  What happened was that
हैं वो फंस जाते हैं। होता क्या है कि
when the British were leaving undivided India, there were
अनडिवाइडेड इंडिया से जब ब्रिटिशर्स जा
two concerned parties, India and Pakistan, that is, Jinnah's Muslim League and Nehruji's Congress, to
मुस्लिम लीग और नेहरू जी की कांग्रेस दो
claim this undivided India.  These
कंसर्न पार्टी थी क्लेम करने के लिए। इन
two parties had to talk among themselves and
दोनों पार्टियों को आपस में बात करके
decide who would get how much share of
फैसला लेना था कि किसके पास कितना पार्ट
this undivided India.  But if
जाएगा इस अनडिवाइडेड इंडिया का। लेकिन अगर
it is legally proved that this Kalat
लीगली ये प्रूव हो जाता है कि जो ये कलात
State is not a part of the British Empire.
स्टेट है ये ब्रिटिश एंपायर का हिस्सा
This was taken by the British Empire for some time through a lease only,
नहीं है। ये तो सिर्फ एक लीज़ के थ्रू कुछ
for which the British used to pay money annually.
जिसके लिए अंग्रेज जो थे वो एनुअली पैसा
So after the British left, the
भी देते थे। तो अंग्रेजों के जाने के बाद
claims of India and Pakistan on the Kalat State would have ended.  And
पाकिस्तान का क्लेम खत्म हो जाता। और
Pakistan had decided that
पाकिस्तान ने यही डिसाइड किया था कि कैसे
before the British left, this Kalat
भी अंग्रेजों के जाने से पहले ये जो कलात
State should somehow prove to be an independent state.
स्टेट है ये एक इंडिपेंडेंट स्टेट साबित
Because as soon as Kalat State is
हो जाए। क्योंकि जैसे ही कलात स्टेट जो है
proved to be an independent state, then
वो एक इंडिपेंडेंट स्टेट साबित होगा तो जो
India's claim on Kalat
इंडिया का क्लेम है वो खत्म हो जाएगा कलात
State will end and later whenever Pakistan
स्टेट के ऊपर से और बाद में पाकिस्तान जब
wants, it can take Kalat State under its control.
चाहेगा वो कलात स्टेट को अपने अंडर में ले
Now your question would be that
लेगा। अब आपका क्वेश्चन ये होगा कि
how was Pakistan so sure that
पाकिस्तान इतना ज्यादा श्योर कैसे था कि
after the British left,
अंग्रेजों के जाने के बाद कलात स्टेट उसको
it would annex the Kalat State to itself.  So see, this
वो अपने साथ जोड़ लेगा। तो देखिए ये जो
was the area of ​​British Balochistan which was
ब्रिटिश बलूचिस्तान वाला एरिया था जो
taken on lease by the British.
अंग्रेजों ने लीज़ पे लिया था। ये
As it is lease, after the British left, whatever was there would have gone
अंग्रेजों के जाने के बाद एज इट इज़ लीज़ जो
with Pakistan.  The
थी वो पाकिस्तान के साथ चली जाती। ये
British had already said this
ब्रिटिशर्स ने पहले ही बोल दिया था
because, firstly, the Muslim population was
क्योंकि एक तो मुस्लिम पॉपुलेशन मेजॉरिटी
in majority here and secondly, it did
में थी यहां पे दूसरा इंडिया से इसका
not share a border with India.  So this pink
बॉर्डर नहीं लगता था। तो ये पिंक वाला जो
area of ​​British Balochistan, the
ब्रिटिश बलूचिस्तान वाला एरिया था ये
lease that was going on after the British left,
अंग्रेजों के जाने के बाद जो लीज चल रही
as it is Pakistan, would have continued that lease. The
थी उस लीज को एज इट इज पाकिस्तान कंटिन्यू
light green area you can see,
करता जो आप लाइट ग्रीन वाला एरिया देख रहे
whose Sardars were associated with Kalat State
हैं जिसके सरदार कलात स्टेट से जुड़े थे
but they ran their own regions separately
लेकिन अलग-अलग अपने-अपने रीजन खुद चलाते
and Jinnah had developed a
थे और ये जो सरदार थे इनसे जिन्ना ने
good bonding with these Sardars. Jinnah had
अच्छी बॉन्डिंग कर ली जिन्ना ने कहीं ना
somewhere convinced these Sardars
कहीं यह जो सरदार थे इनको कन्विंस कर लिया
that after the British left, Pakistan would
था कि अंग्रेजों के जाने के बाद पाकिस्तान
become an Islamic country and if you
एक इस्लामिक देश बनेगा और अगर आप
join Pakistan, the first thing
पाकिस्तान के साथ जुड़ोगे तो पहली चीज तो
you will get is your autonomy.  The rest of your
आपको अपनी ऑटोनोमी मिलेगी। बाकी आपकी
identity and culture will function
आइडेंटिटी और कल्चर जो है वो पाकिस्तान के
better by connecting with Pakistan.  And the
साथ जुड़ के ज्यादा सही से चलेगी। और
Sardars were somehow getting influenced by
सरदार जो थे वो कहीं ना कहीं इन्फ्लुएंस
this statement of Jinnah because the
हो रहे थे जिन्ना की इस बात से क्योंकि
leaders of Kalat State, this dark green area, were talking about
जो एरिया है इनके जो लीडर थे वो आजादी के
making Kalat State a secular country after independence.
बाद कलात स्टेट को एक सेकुलर देश बनाने की
So Jinnah was confident of all these things
बातें कर रहे थे। तो इन सब चीजों से
once it was
जिन्ना को यकीन था कि एक बार इसको इंडिया
legally removed from India's influence.
के इन्फ्लुएंस से लीगली दूर कर दो। उसके
After that, the Kalat State will be
बाद जो कलात स्टेट होगा उसको अपने अंडर
easily taken under its control.  And because
बड़े आराम से ले लिया जाएगा। और क्योंकि
this thing about Pakistan was suiting the British also, the
पाकिस्तान की ये चीज ब्रिटिशर्स को भी सूट
British were also indirectly
कर रही थी तो ब्रिटिशर्स भी इनडायरेक्टली
in favor of it.  So
कहीं ना कहीं इसके फेवर में थे। तो इसके
what did Jinnah do after this?  Khan of Kalat
बाद जिन्ना ने क्या किया? खान ऑफ कलात की
said that it should be like an independent country
जो बात थी कि एक इंडिपेंडेंट देश की तरह
after the British leave.
इसको होना चाहिए जब अंग्रेज चले जाए। इसको
Supported this.  Jinnah said that Kalat State had
सपोर्ट किया। जिन्ना ने कहा कि कलात स्टेट
no link with the British.
जो है उसका ब्रिटिशर्स से कोई लिंक नहीं
They have just signed a lease and a treaty.
है। उन्होंने बस एक लीज़ और ट्रीटी कर रखी
Therefore Kalat State should be an independent
है। इसलिए कलात स्टेट को एक इंडिपेंडेंट
country.  Now after hearing this from Jinnah, the
कंट्री होना चाहिए। अब जिन्ना की इस चीज
Khan of Kalat became very happy
को सुनके खान ऑफ़ कलात जो थे वो बहुत खुश
that this is the only person who is
होते हैं कि ये अकेला आदमी है जो मेरे को
supporting me.  Now Jinnah was
सपोर्ट कर रहा है। अब जिन्ना जो थे वो
also a lawyer.  So the Khan of Kalat Mir Ahmed Yar
लॉयर भी थे। तो खान ऑफ़ कलात मीर अहमद यार
Khan made Jinnah a legal advisor of the entire Kalat State in the year 1946.   The
खान ने ईयर 1946 में जिन्ना को पूरे कलात
Khan of Kalat
खान ऑफ कलात ने जिन्ना को ये
gave the responsibility to Jinnah that Kalat State
रिस्पांसिबिलिटी दी कि कलात स्टेट को एज
should be an independent state.
एन इंडिपेंडेंट स्टेट होना चाहिए। इस केस
You will represent this case before the British.
को अंग्रेजों के सामने आप रिप्रेजेंट
And as soon as Jinnah was made the legal advisor,
करोगे। और जैसे ही जिन्ना को लीगल एडवाइजर
Jinnah made a memorandum in March 1946
बनाया गया तो जिन्ना ने मार्च 1946 को एक
in which he mentioned all the things that
मेमोरेंडम बनाया जिसमें सारी चीजें मेंशन
Kalat State was
करी उन्होंने कि कलात स्टेट ब्रिटिशर्स के
linked with the treaty and lease agreement with the Britishers.
साथ ट्रीटी और लीज़ एग्रीमेंट के साथ जुड़ा
And also added references to the entire treaty.
है। और रेफरेंस भी ऐड किए पूरी ट्रीटी के।
And in this memorandum, a demand was made that
और इस मेमोरेंडम में डिमांड करी गई कि
when the British leave, the Kalat State should be
ब्रिटिशर्स जब जाए तो कलात स्टेट जो है वो
an independent state.  And after
एक इंडिपेंडेंट स्टेट होना चाहिए। और यह
preparing all this,
सारा कुछ बना के ब्रिटिशर्स के जो कैबिनेट
it was submitted to the Cabinet Mission of the British.  And when
मिशन था उसको ये सबमिट कर दिया गया। और जब
this memorandum was submitted, the discussion
ये मेमोरेंडम सबमिट हुआ तो ये डिस्कशन
started that this Kalat State will
स्टार्ट हो गया कि ये जो कलात स्टेट है ये
remain independent after the British left.  And after this, the British
रहेगा। और फिर इसके बाद ब्रिटिशर्स ने जो
thought that the area of ​​British Balochistan, which they had taken on
सोचा था कि ब्रिटिश बलूचिस्तान वाला जो
lease from the Khan of Kalas, they would
एरिया है जो लीज़ पे ले रखा था खान ऑफ़ कलास
give it to Pakistan when leaving.  So the
से उसको जाते टाइम पाकिस्तान को देंगे। तो
British started work for that also.
उसके लिए भी ब्रिटिशर्स ने काम स्टार्ट कर
What did the British do?  On the 29th of
दिया। ब्रिटिशर्स ने क्या किया? 29th ऑफ
June 1947, there was a courageous Jirga tribe of this area
जून 1947 को इस एरिया की साहसी जिरगा
which was not an elected body.
ट्राइब थी जो कि ये कोई इलेक्टेड बॉडी
But the British had appointed them for
नहीं थी। लेकिन ब्रिटिशर्स ने इनको अपॉइंट
different tasks.  So, somewhere or the
कर रखा था अलग-अलग काम के लिए। तो कहीं ना
other, these people were loyal to the British.  We used to
कहीं ये लोग ब्रिटिशर्स के लॉयल थे। इनके
act according to them.  They were called and the
हिसाब से चलते थे। इनको बुलाया और इस
non-official
इसके म्युनिसिपालिटी के नॉन ऑफिशियल
members of the municipality of the British Balochistan area, that is, the Kota area, were also called and a voting was conducted as to
मेंबर्स भी बुलाए और एक वोटिंग करा दी कि
where British Balochistan should be merged.
ब्रिटिश बलूचिस्तान को कहां पे जोड़ना
Now, regarding this voting, the leadership of Kalat State
चाहिए। अब इस वोटिंग को लेके कलात स्टेट
became very angry that you did not involve any of the Kalat leadership.  No
में हुई कि आपने किसी भी कलात की लीडरशिप
referendum was
को इन्वॉल्व नहीं किया। कोई रेफरेंडम नहीं
held and voting was done across the state without asking.
कराया और पूरे स्टेट में बिना पूछे वोटिंग
And when the results of this voting came,
कराई। और इस वोटिंग का जब रिजल्ट आया तो
it was decided that after the departure of the British,
ये डिसाइड हुआ कि ब्रिटिशर्स के जाने के
this area which the British had
बाद ये जो एरिया है जो ब्रिटिशर्स ने लीज़
taken on lease, British Balochistan, as it is, will
पे लिया है ब्रिटिश बलूचिस्तान वाला ये एज
go to Pakistan.  Now, regarding this issue, the
इट इज़ पाकिस्तान को चला जाएगा। अब इस चीज
Baloch tribe of the Kalat
को लेके जो बलोच ट्राइब थी जो कलात रीजन
region opposed it a lot.
वाला जो एरिया था इसको बहुत अपोज किया।
He said that the British had leased it.
उन्होंने कहा कि अंग्रेजों ने तो लीज़ कर
He was not the owner of this area.
रखी थी। वो इस एरिया के कोई ओनर तो थे
So what right do they have to
नहीं। तो उनका क्या हक बनता है कि वो इस
lease this area to Pakistan also?
एरिया को पाकिस्तान के साथ भी लीज पे दे
So when all these things were going on,
दे। तो जब ये सारी बातें चल रही थी तो
then next comes the date Fourth of August
इसके बाद फिर डेट आती है फोर्थ ऑफ अगस्त
1947.  Kalat State should become independent on this day.  There was
1947। इस दिन कलात स्टेट इंडिपेंडेंट होना
talk about this everywhere
चाहिए। इसको लेके हर तरफ बात तो हो ही रही
and on the same day Lord Mountbatten, Jinnah and
थी और इसी दिन लॉर्ड माउंटबेटन जिन्ना और
Khan of Kalat held a round table conference
खान ऑफ कलात एक राउंड टेबल कॉन्फ्रेंस
and here it was decided that the
करते हैं और यहां से ये डिसाइड होता है कि
status of Kalat State would remain the same as it was in the year 1838.  This
कलात स्टेट जो है जो ईयर 1838 का स्टेटस
means
था वही स्टेटस रहेगा कलात स्टेट का। यानी
that Kalat State will
कि कलात स्टेट जो है वो इंडिपेंडेंट
remain independent.  Now the Khan of Kalat was very happy with the decision taken by all of them together.
रहेगा। अब ये जो सबने मिलकर डिसीजन बनाया
He said, do one more thing.
हुए। इन्होंने कहा कि एक काम और कर दीजिए।
A written agreement should also be made that
एक रिटन एग्रीमेंट भी कर लेना चाहिए कि
Kalat State will remain independent.
कलात स्टेट जो है वो इंडिपेंडेंट रहेगा।
Now, this written agreement creates
अब इस रिटन एग्रीमेंट को लेके तो
problem for Pakistan.  So the
पाकिस्तान के लिए दिक्कत हो जाती है। तो
British
ब्रिटिशर्स ने इंडिपेंडेंट कलात स्टेट के
gave the declaration for the Independent Kalat State but did
लिए डिक्लेरेशन तो दे दिया लेकिन रिटन
not sign the written agreement.  He
एग्रीमेंट पे साइन नहीं किया। उन्होंने ये
said that it does not have any meaning now.
कहा कि अब इसका कोई मतलब नहीं रह गया।
After this the Khan of Kalat said that you should
इसके बाद खान ऑफ़ कलात ने ये कहा कि आप
at least make a public announcement.
एटलीस्ट पब्लिक अनाउंसमेंट कर दीजिए।
But the British refused to do that too.
लेकिन ब्रिटिशर्स ने उसके लिए भी मना कर
And then the Khan of Kalat did
दिया। और फिर खान ऑफ कलात ने इसको बहुत
not make it a big issue that our area
बड़ा इशू नहीं बनाया कि हमारा जो एरिया
, our culture, our identity will
है, हमारा जो कल्चर है, हमारी आइडेंटिटी
now remain in an independent country.
है, अब वो एक इंडिपेंडेंट देश में रहेगी।
And on the same day i.e. Fourth of August 1947,
और सेम डे यानी कि फोर्थ ऑफ अगस्त 1947 को
Kalat State and Jinnah of Pakistan
कलात स्टेट और पाकिस्तान के जिन्ना ने एक
signed a Stand Still Agreement.
स्टैंड स्टिल एग्रीमेंट साइन किया। इस
In this agreement, Pakistan officially
एग्रीमेंट में पाकिस्तान ने ऑफिशियली कलात
recognised Kalat State as an independent state.  And
स्टेट को एक इंडिपेंडेंट स्टेट माना। और
as soon as this happened, India's role
जैसे ही ये हुआ, अब यहां से इंडिया का रोल
ends here.  And
खत्म हो जाता है। और ये स्टैंड स्टिल
if you look up the date of this stand still agreement
एग्रीमेंट की जो डेट है ये आप अगर इंटरनेट
on the internet, it will find 11th of August
पे देखोगे तो कहीं पे 11th ऑफ़ अगस्त भी
written somewhere.  But the announcement was made on 11th of August.
लिखा होगा। लेकिन 11th ऑफ अगस्त को
Actually
अनाउंसमेंट हुई थी। एक्चुअल में फोर्थ ऑफ
it was signed on the Fourth of August.  So Pakistan was
अगस्त को ही ये साइन हुआ था। तो पाकिस्तान
very happy about this because it had
इस चीज को लेके बहुत खुश था क्योंकि उसने
signed the Stand Still Agreement
स्टैंड स्टिल एग्रीमेंट साइन कर लिया था
and because of this India was out of the whole game.
और इसकी वजह से इंडिया जो है इस पूरे गेम
Otherwise, if this agreement had
से बाहर हो गया था। वरना अगर ये एग्रीमेंट
not been signed, the same
साइन नहीं होता तो वही कश्मीर वाली जैसी
situation like that of Kashmir could have arisen again between India and Pakistan.
सिचुएशन इंडिया और पाकिस्तान के बीच में
Now
फिर से बन सकती थी। अब इसके बाद अंग्रेजों
after the departure of the British, India got independence on 15th of August 1947.
के जाने के बाद जैसे 15th ऑफ अगस्त 1947
Pakistan
इंडिया को आजादी मिली। पाकिस्तान अलग
became a separate state.  Same day Khan of Kalat Mir Ahmed
स्टेट बना। सेम डे खान ऑफ कलात मीर अहमद
Yar Khan also announced his independence.
यार खान ने भी अपनी इंडिपेंडेंस अनाउंस कर
And then about a
दी। और फिर इस अनाउंसमेंट के करीब एक
month after this announcement, that is, on 12th of September 1947, the
महीने बाद यानी कि 12th ऑफ़ सितंबर 1947 को
British gave a small official
ब्रिटिशर्स ने एक छोटा सा ऑफिशियल
statement.  He said that the
स्टेटमेंट दिया। उन्होंने कहा कि ये जो
Khan of Kalat Mir Ahmed Yar Khan has
खान ऑफ कलात मीर अहमद यार खान ने ये जो
announced the independence of the Kalat State,
कलात स्टेट की इंडिपेंडेंस अनाउंस की है
he has done so but the Kalat State is
ये कर तो दी है इन्होंने लेकिन कलात स्टेट
not in a position to handle international responsibilities right now.  Now
संभालने की सिचुएशन में नहीं है अभी। अब
this statement
ये जो स्टेटमेंट है ये सुनने में तो बहुत
seems very normal to hear but it has a lot of meaning.
नॉर्मल लग रहा है लेकिन इसके बहुत मायने
This entire statement
हैं। ये पूरा स्टेटमेंट पाकिस्तान के
went in support of Pakistan and after this statement,
सपोर्ट में गया और इस स्टेटमेंट के बाद
Pakistan started putting pressure on Khan
पाकिस्तान ने प्रेशर बनाना चालू किया खान
of Kalat to join Pakistan.
ऑफ कलात पे कि पाकिस्तान से जुड़ जाओ।
Pakistan did two things.  Firstly, they
पाकिस्तान ने दो चीजें की। एक तो कलात
started preparing to attack Kalat State
स्टेट पे हमला करने के लिए तैयारी शुरू कर
and slowly started deploying the army
दी और धीरे-धीरे करके आर्मी डिप्लॉय करना
and along with that, as I
स्टार्ट कर दिया और साथ में जो पहले मैंने
told you earlier, Jinnah started talking to the leaders of the Makran,
बताया था कि कलात स्टेट के साथ जो मकरान
Lasbela and Kharan areas whose
लसबेला और खरान वाला जो एरिया है जिनके
chiefs had joined Kalat State, to
सरदार कलात स्टेट के साथ जुड़ गए थे इनके
join Pakistan.  Now after
दिया था कि पाकिस्तान से जुड़ जाओ। अब ये
seeing all these things, the Khan of Kalat
सारी चीजें देख के जो खान ऑफ़ कलात थे
immediately
उन्होंने दिसंबर 1947 में ये तुरंत
went to the British in December 1947 and said that this Pakistan is
ब्रिटिशर्स के पास गए कि ये जो पाकिस्तान
asking to join us.  He is
है ये हमारे साथ जुड़ने के लिए बोल रहा
planning to attack us.
है। हम पे हमला करने की प्लानिंग कर रहा
So we also need military support.
है। तो हमें भी मिलिट्री सपोर्ट चाहिए।
But the British flatly refused.
लेकिन ब्रिटिशर्स ने साफ मना कर दिया।
After this the Khan of Kalad
इसके बाद खान ऑफ़ कलाद जो थे वो
went to Afghanistan.  He even
अफगानिस्तान के पास गए। यहां तक कि इंडिया
went to India.  But Afghanistan and
के पास भी गए। लेकिन अफगानिस्तान और
India also refused to support.
इंडिया ने भी सपोर्ट करने से मना कर दिया।
And then in the beginning of January 1948,
और फिर जनवरी 1948 के स्टार्टिंग में
Pakistan talked to the leaders of Makran, Lujbela and Kharan and made
पाकिस्तान ने मकरान, लज़बेला और खरान के
a deal
जो लीडर्स थे इनसे बात करी एक डील करी
in which it was decided that Pakistan would
जिसमें ये हुआ कि पाकिस्तान जो है इनको
provide financial support to them.  He
फाइनेंसियल सपोर्ट देगा। इनके जो सरदार
will make their leader the state head of Pakistan.
हैं उनको स्टेट हेड बनाएगा पाकिस्तान का।
Their culture and identity will never be
इनके कल्चर और आइडेंटिटी को कभी भी नहीं
tampered with.  After saying all these things,
छेड़ेगा। ये सारी चीजें बोलने के बाद 17
Pakistan annexed them on 17 March 1948.
मार्च 1948 में पाकिस्तान ने इनको जोड़
As soon as all these chieftains
लिया। जैसे ही ये सारे सरदार पाकिस्तान से
met Pakistan, the area of ​​Kalat State got
मिले, जो कलात स्टेट वाला जो एरिया था वो
trapped from all sides.  If you
चारों तरफ से फंस गया। आप अगर इसको मैप
see it on the map, it has become like a landlocked area.
में देखोगे तो एक लैंड लॉक एरिया की तरह
Completely isolated politically.
बन गया। पॉलिटिकली पूरी तरीके से आइसोलेट
What was British Balochistan was
हो गया। ब्रिटिश बलूचिस्तान जो था वो पहले
already with Pakistan.  After getting this, the
से ही पाकिस्तान के पास था। ये मिलने के
entire area came under Pakistan
बाद पूरा का पूरा एरिया पाकिस्तान के पास
and then exactly 10 days after this,
आ गया और फिर इसके ठीक 10 दिन बाद
Major General Mohammad Akbar Khan of Pakistan
पाकिस्तान के मेजर जनरल मोहम्मद अकबर खान
started entering Kalat with the Pakistan Army and the destroyers and warships of Pakistan Navy were
घुसना स्टार्ट किया और पाकिस्तान की नेवी
deployed at the ports of Pasni and Jiwani
और जिवानी के जो पोर्ट्स थे वहां पे तैनात
and after surrounding him from all sides, they took the Khan of
कर दिया और चारों तरफ से घेर के ये खान ऑफ
Kalat to Karachi and after getting the
कलात को कराची ले गए और यहां पे
documents signed here, they
डॉक्यूमेंट पे साइन करा के पूरा का पूरा
took the entire area under Pakistan and now after
एरिया पाकिस्तान में ले लिया और अब ये
bringing this entire area under Pakistan, it was
पूरा एरिया पाकिस्तान में लाके इसका का
named
नाम रखा गया
Balochistan.  Now see, Pakistan had
बलूचिस्तान। अब देखिए पाकिस्तान ने खान ऑफ
forcibly got the documents signed from Khan of Kalat Mir Ahmed Yar Khan.
कलात मीर अहमद यार खान से जबरदस्ती
But
डॉक्यूमेंट तो साइन करा लिए थे। लेकिन
soon after this a problem started.
इसके तुरंत बाद एक दिक्कत स्टार्ट हो गई।
Prince Abdul Karim, brother of the Khan of Kalat, became
खान ऑफ कलात के जो भाई थे प्रिंस अब्दुल
very angry
करीम ये बहुत ज्यादा गुस्सा हो जाते हैं
that Pakistan had betrayed him.  So his
कि ये पाकिस्तान ने धोखा किया है। तो इनके
brother gathered 100 to 150 people with him in April 1948.  They
भाई अप्रैल 1948 को 100 से 150 आदमी अपने
form a Baloch National Liberation Committee and
लिबरेशन कमेटी बनाते हैं और गोरिल्ला वॉर
start a guerilla war against the Pakistan Army.  They go to the
स्टार्ट कर देते हैं पाकिस्तान आर्मी के
South West Balochistan area near the Afghanistan border,
जो साउथ वेस्ट बलूचिस्तान वाला जो एरिया
Kharan Hills and Nochki Hills,
था खरान हिल्स और नोचकी जो पहाड़ियां थी
and start
वहां जाके ये सब बैठ जाते हैं और
attacking Pakistan forces back to back and demand that they
पाकिस्तान फोर्सेस पे बैक टू बैक हमला
return their state to them.  Now see, even though these people were less in number
वापस करो। अब देखिए भले ये लोग नंबर्स में
but they knew every inch of the area,
कम थे लेकिन पूरे एरिया के चप्पे-चप्पे को
so no matter how big the army was,
ये लोग जानते थे तो कितनी भी बड़ी आर्मी
they would have a lot of trouble
रहती थी उनको बहुत परेशानी होती थी इनसे
dealing with them.  These one or two people would come down from the hill,
डील करने में। ये एक-दो लोग पहाड़ी से उतर
attack and then hide in the hills.
कर हमला करते थे और फिर पहाड़ियों में ही
So this thing had
छुप जाते थे। तो इस चीज से पाकिस्तान की
become a thorn in the side of Pakistan.  No solution was
नाक में दम हो गया था। कोई सॉल्यूशन नहीं
found.  Then what happened was that on
मिल रहा था। फिर क्या हुआ कि 8th ऑफ जुलाई
this day of 8th July 1948, Pakistan forces
1948 को इस दिन पाकिस्तान फोर्सेस ने
started negotiations with Prince Abdul Karim
प्रिंस अब्दुल करीम से बातचीत स्टार्ट की
and swore on the Quran that you all come down and
और कुरान की कसम खाई कि आप लोग नीचे आओ
surrender, we will forgive you.  Please bring down the
सरेंडर करो हम आपको माफ कर देंगे। आपकी जो
rest of your tribes who are sitting up there as
बाकी ट्राइब्स है वो जो लोग ऊपर बैठे हैं
well.  There will
उनको भी आप नीचे लेके आओ। कोई दिक्कत नहीं
be no problem.  You should stop this fight.  Now all these
होगी। इस लड़ाई को आप बंद करो। अब ये सारे
people come down after hearing this.
लोग ये बात सुन के नीचे आ जाते हैं।
Because swearing on the Quran is a
क्योंकि कुरान की कसम जो है मुस्लिम्स के
big deal for Muslims.  But as soon as
लिए बहुत बड़ी बात होती है। लेकिन जैसे ही
these people came down, they denied it.
ये लोग नीचे उतरे तो ये मुकर गए। इन सबको
They arrested all of them and put them in Quetta and Marsh
पकड़ के इन्होंने क्वेटा और मार्श की जो
jails and on 10th
जेल थी उसमें डाल दिया और फिर 10th ऑफ
December 1948, they were sentenced to 10 years of imprisonment.   Every
दिसंबर 1948 को 10 साल की सजा दे दी इनको।
common Baloch considers this incident to be a
जो आम बलोच है इस इंसिडेंट को अपने लिए एक
big betrayal for him that how could
बहुत बड़ा धोखा मानता है कि कुरान की कसम
they take such a false oath on the Quran.  Now
ऐसे कैसे इन्होंने झूठी खा ली। अब
as Pakistan got rid of this problem,
जैसे-जैसे इस मुसीबत से पीछा छूटा
another problem arose on 14th October 1955.  What happened was that
दूसरी मुसीबत खड़ी हो गई। हुआ क्या कि उस
at that time Pakistan was divided into two parts.
टाइम पे पाकिस्तान दो पार्ट में डिवाइडेड
One East Pakistan i.e. today's
था। एक ईस्ट पाकिस्तान यानी कि आज का
Bangladesh.  Second, West Pakistan.  There were
बांग्लादेश। दूसरा वेस्ट पाकिस्तान। वेस्ट
four provinces within West Pakistan.  Sindh
पाकिस्तान के अंदर चार प्रोविंस थे। सिंध
Province, NWFP Province, Punjab
प्रोविंस, एनडब्ल्यूएफपी प्रोविंस, पंजाब
Province and Balochistan Province.  So,
प्रोविंस और बलूचिस्तान प्रोविंस। तो
through the One Unit policy, Pakistan
पाकिस्तान वन यूनिट पॉलिसी के थ्रू ये जो
wanted to maintain a single identity of West Pakistan by combining the four provinces of West Pakistan.  And Pakistan
की आइडेंटिटी रखना चाहता था। और पाकिस्तान
also implemented this one unit policy.  What I
ने इस वन यूनिट पॉलिसी को इंप्लीमेंट भी
mean to say is that these different
कर दिया। कहने का मतलब है कि यह अलग-अलग
provinces which had their own separate authority
प्रोविंस जिनकी अपनी अलग-अलग अथॉरिटी
identities will now be run by a central authority
आइडेंटिटी थी वो सब एक सेंट्रल अथॉरिटी से
and in this central authority,
अब चलेगी और ये जो सेंट्रल अथॉरिटी थे
most of them were the leaders of Punjab province.
इसमें ज्यादातर पंजाब प्रोविंस जो था उसके
Now this idea of ​​one unit system was a
लीडर थे। अब ये जो वन यूनिट सिस्टम का
direct threat
आईडिया था ये डायरेक्ट थ्रेट था
to Balochistan.  The problem with this was that
बलूचिस्तान के लिए। इससे दिक्कत ये थी कि
Balochistan had its own identity, history, and
बलूचिस्तान की अपनी आइडेंटिटी, हिस्ट्री,
even constitution.  With the advent of this one unit
इवन कॉन्स्टिट्यूशन तक था। इस वन यूनिट
system, their identity was being lost.
सिस्टम के आने से इनकी आइडेंटिटी खत्म हो
Even the name was disappearing.
रही थी। यहां तक कि नाम तक खत्म हो रहा
Those who brought the One Unit policy,
था। जो ये वन यूनिट पॉलिसी लाए थे इससे
their name became West Pakistan.  So the
इनका नाम वेस्ट पाकिस्तान हो गया था। तो
name Balochistan was officially
जो बलूचिस्तान नाम था वो ऑफिशियली
disappearing.  Now what happened was that the
डिसअपीयर हो रहा था। अब इससे हुआ ये कि जो
Baloch had merged
बलोच थे जिन्होंने इसलिए मर्जर किया था
with Pakistan so that they could run their own separate
पाकिस्तान के साथ कि वो अलग से अपना एक
system.  He became a second class
सिस्टम चला पाएंगे। वो एक सेकंड क्लास
citizen.  Their entire
सिटीजन बन गए। पूरा का पूरा जो उनका अलग
separate political representation did
से पॉलिटिकल रिप्रेजेंटेशन था वो बचा ही
not remain.  The Punjab leadership of Pakistan
नहीं। पाकिस्तान की पंजाब लीडरशिप सब
started handling everything.  So protests started all over Balochistan regarding this.   The
संभालने लगी। तो इसको लेके पूरे
matter escalated so much that by the year 1958,
बात इतनी बढ़ गई कि ईयर 1958 आते-आते
Pakistan had to impose martial law in the entire area.
पाकिस्तान को इस पूरे एरिया में मार्शल लॉ
So because of the imposition of martial law, the
तो मार्शल लॉ लगने की वजह से जो
people of Balochistan also lost their rights.
बलूचिस्तान के जो लोग थे उनके राइट्स भी
Now what happened was that there was
चले गए। अब हुआ क्या कि बलूचिस्तान के
a poisonous tribe in the Jalavan region of Balochistan.
जालावान रीजन में एक ज़हरी ट्राइब थी।
An 80 year old man named Nawab Noorus Khan
उसमें एक 80 साल का आदमी नवाब नूरूस खान
lived there and he became adamant.  They
यह रहते थे और यह अड़ गए। पूरी पाकिस्तान
stood against the entire Pakistan force, and
फ़ोर्स के अगेंस्ट में खड़े हो गए और नवाब
seeing Nawab Noors Khan, the young
नूरस खान को देख के जो आसपास के जो यंग
Baloch in the vicinity also came to fight with them.  Achha is
बलोच थे वो भी इनके साथ लड़ने आ गए। अच्छा
a specialty of Balochs and is
बलोचों की एक खासियत है और जो कि पूरी
famous all over the world.  Even today,
दुनिया में मशहूर है। इवन आज की डेट में
if you see, whenever there is a revolt,
भी अगर आप देखोगे जब भी कोई रिवॉल्ट होता
anything happens, the
है कुछ भी होता है तो रिवॉल्ट करने के लिए
leadership that is there to revolt does not fight itself, nor does it
जो लीडरशिप होती है वो खुद नहीं लड़ती ना
send its children, nor does it
ही अपने बच्चों को भेजती है ना ही अपने
send its family members.  Actually
फैमिली मेंबर्स को भेजती है। एक्चुअल में
poor people go to fight.  But the Baloch
गरीब लोग लड़ने जाते हैं। लेकिन बलोच जो
leaders always go ahead and fight.   I
हैं इनके लीडर हमेशा आगे जाके लड़ते हैं।
fight myself.  They also make their children and their family
खुद लड़ते हैं। अपने बच्चे और अपनी फैमिली
fight later on.  So Nawab
को भी आगे चलके लड़वाते हैं। तो नवाब
Nooruls Khan also
नूरुल्स खान जो थे तो इन्होंने भी अपनी
started the revolt along with his entire family.
पूरी फैमिली के साथ ही रिवॉल्ट शुरू किया।
So in this way 140 people joined him.
तो ऐसे करके इनके साथ 140 लोग मिल गए थे।
He had started a general struggle against Pakistan.  What did these people do?
थी इन्होंने। इन लोगों ने क्या किया था?
Koem was a mountain of murd.
कोएम मुरद के पहाड़ थे। जलावान रीजन के जो
They went and settled in the poisonous hills of Jalavan region.
जहरी हिल्स थे उनमें जाके ये बैठ गए थे।
And in the same manner as the
और उसी तरीके से जैसे गोरिल्ला वॉरफेयर
Baloch had been carrying out guerilla warfare till now, they would come down and
बलोच अभी तक करते आए थे उसी की तरह नीचे आ
attack the Pakistani forces.  So the
के पाकिस्तान फोर्सेस पे हमला करते थे। तो
same thing happened with them too.  The Pakistani
इनके साथ भी वही चीज हुई। पाकिस्तान
forces got tired of fighting.
फोर्सेस जो थी वो परेशान हो गई लड़-लड़
So Pakistan made a deal with them also.
के। तो पाकिस्तान ने इनके साथ भी एक डील
So he said that you do
की। तो इन्होंने कहा कि आप वन यूनिट
not believe in the one unit policy.  Do
पॉलिसी को मानते नहीं हो। इसके लिए आप
n't fight for this.  We will remove this and forgive you all.
लड़ो मत। हम इसको हटा देते हैं और आप सबको
Here also he
माफी दे देते हैं। यहां भी इन्होंने कुरान
took oath on the Quran.  As soon as he came down he was arrested and
की कसम खाई। जैसे ही ये नीचे आए इनको पकड़
put in jail and was hanged along with
के जेल में डाल दिया गया और 15th ऑफ जुलाई
Nawab Noorus Khan's son and
1960 को नवाब नूरुस खान के बेटे और
others on 15th of July 1960.  But this
बाकियों के साथ दे दी गई। लेकिन इससे आम
further enraged the general public.
जनता और भड़क गई। पूरे बलूचिस्तान में
Small groups were formed all over Balochistan and
छोटे-छोटे अलग-अलग ग्रुप बन गए और
started attacking Pakistani forces, police posts, railways, telecommunications, government supply lines etc.
लाइन सब पर हमला करना स्टार्ट किया।
Pakistan also responded by carrying out air
पाकिस्तान ने भी इसके जवाब में एयर
strikes etc. and a deadlock like
स्ट्राइक वगैरह करी और जब एक डेड लॉक जैसी
situation was created because everyone in the mountains
सिचुएशन बन गई क्योंकि पहाड़ में
knew everything about it.  It became
चप्पाचप्पा जानते थे। पाकिस्तान फोर्सेस
very difficult for Pakistani forces to fight them.
के लिए इनसे लड़ना बहुत मुश्किल हो जाता
So, in frustration, on the First of July 1970,
था। तो थक हार के फर्स्ट ऑफ जुलाई 1970
General Ya Khan ended the One Unit Policy.
में जनरल या खान ने वन यूनिट पॉलिसी को
Now when this policy was removed, the
खत्म किया। अब जब ये पॉलिसी हटी तो सेवंथ
first general elections were to be held in Pakistan on 7th of December 1970.
ऑफ दिसंबर 1970 को पाकिस्तान में पहली बार
So these general
जनरल इलेक्शन होने वाले थे। तो ये जो जनरल
elections were to be held in all the provinces.
इलेक्शन होने थे ये सारे के सारे प्रोविंस
So it had to happen inside Balochistan too.
में होने थे। तो बलूचिस्तान के अंदर भी
So what the Balochis did was that they
होने थे। तो बलोचियों ने क्या किया कि जो
voted for their local parties like NAP, JUI and got them elected and at the same time,
इनको वोट देकर जितवा दिया और सेम टाइम पे
East Pakistan,
पाकिस्तान के हाथ से ईस्ट पाकिस्तान यानी
which is today's Bangladesh, also slipped out of the hands of Pakistan.
कि आज का जो बांग्लादेश है वो भी निकल
Now as soon as East
गया। अब जैसे ही पाकिस्तान से ईस्ट
Pakistan i.e. Bangladesh separated from Pakistan.  So the
पाकिस्तान यानी कि बांग्लादेश अलग हुआ। तो
entire constitution of Pakistan ended
पाकिस्तान का पूरा कॉन्स्टिट्यूशन तो खत्म
and a new constitution had to be made.  So
हुआ और नया कॉन्स्टिट्यूशन बनना था। तो
for this, the local parties of Balochistan
इसके लिए बलूचिस्तान की जो लोकल पार्टियां
were NAP and JUI.  The support of the one who had won the election was
थी एनएपी और जेयूआई। जो इलेक्शन जीती थी
also needed.
उसके सपोर्ट की भी जरूरत थी। थोड़े दिन
Bangladesh had separated just a few days ago.  So now
पहले ही बांग्लादेश अलग हुआ था। तो अब
Pakistan shows some leniency.  So
पाकिस्तान थोड़ा नरमी दिखाता है। तो यहां
here Zulfikar Ali Bhutto
पे जुल्फिकार अली भुट्टो जो थे उनको
needed the support of the winning parties in Balochistan to make the constitution.  So Zulfikar Ali
उनका सपोर्ट चाहिए था। तो जुल्फिकार अली
Bhutto influenced the
भुट्टो जो थे वो बलोचिस्तान की जो
political parties of Balochistan.
पॉलिटिकल पार्टियां थी उनको अपने
Baloch leader
इन्फ्लुएंस में लिया। बलोचों के सरदार
Ataullah Mengal was made the CM of Buchistan.
अताउल्ला मैंगल को बूचिस्तान का सीएम
Ghosh Bakhsh was made the governor
बनाया। घोष बख्श जो थे उनको गवर्नर बनाया
and the
और बलोचिस्तान के जो बाकी हिस्सों में भी
different people who lived in the rest of Balochistan were made heads of that area.  The
जो अलग-अलग लोग जीते थे उनको उस एरिया का
Baloch were very happy with this
हेड बनाया। बलोच इससे बहुत ज्यादा खुश हुए
and the winning Baloch parties gave the kind of support that Pakistan needed in making the constitution
और कॉन्स्टिट्यूशन बनाने में पाकिस्तान को
and after all this was
जीती हुई पार्टियों ने दिया और ये सब
settled, Zulfikar Ali Bhutto
निपटने के बाद जुल्फिकार अली भुट्टो जो थे
became the PM of Pakistan and
वो पीएम बनते हैं पाकिस्तान के और उसके
a few days after that, i.e. on 10th February
कुछ ही दिन बाद यानी के 10th ऑफ फरवरी
1973, the political party of Balochistan,
1973 को बलोचिस्तान की जो पॉलिटिकल पार्टी
NAP, was banned and a full
थी एनएपी उसको बैन कर दिया गया और फुल
scale military operation was started.   The
स्केल मिलिट्री ऑपरेशन चालू कर दिया गया।
army settled in every nook and corner of Balochistan.
बलोचिस्तान के चप्पे-चप्पे पे आर्मी आके
Bhutto said that this NAP
बैठ गई भुट्टो ने कहा कि यह जो एनएपी जो
political party of the Balochis was
पॉलिटिकल पार्टी है बलोचियों की यह बाहर
committing treason and planning in connivance with foreign countries.
की कंट्रीियों के साथ मिलके देशद्रोह कर
And this
रही थी, प्लानिंग कर रही थी। और यह जो
entire military operation took place in this entire
पूरा मिलिट्री ऑपरेशन किया गया इस पूरे
area, in which thousands of people lost their lives.
एरिया के अंदर हजारों लोगों की जान गई।
Crackdown started on Baloch journalists, students, activists and Sardars.
एक्टिविस्ट, सरदार सब पे क्रैकडाउन चालू
Now after this,
हो गया। अब इसके बाद जगह-जगह पे
guerilla warfare started at various places in Balochistan.
बलोचिस्तान के अंदर गोरिल्ला वॉरफेयर शुरू
Somehow,
गया। जैसे तैसे करके कुछ टाइम के लिए
Ziaul Haq made a basic deal for some time.  After
जियाउल हक ने एक बेसिक डील करी। जितने भी
talking to all the Sardars,
सरदार थे उनसे बातचीत करके गवर्नमेंट में
high posts in the government were given to them.  So
ऊंची-ऊंची पोस्ट दी गई। तो काफी टाइम तक
this thing remained true for quite some time.  But by the year 2000, the
ये चीज सही रही। लेकिन ईयर 2000 आते-आते
Balochs again set up a strong army.
फिर से बलोचों ने एक स्ट्रांग आर्मी सेटअप
Balochistan Liberation Army
किया। बलोचिस्तान लिबरेशन आर्मी
BLA.  This BALA which was created by the Balochs was
बीएलए। ये जो बीएएलए बलोचों ने बनाई थी,
their most organised method of fighting till now.
ये अभी तक का इनका सबसे ऑर्गेनाइज्ड लड़ने
And what was happening in Pakistan at this time was
का तरीका था। और इसी टाइम पे पाकिस्तान
that Balochistan was a
में क्या हो रहा था कि बलूचिस्तान का एक
strategic area.  So Pakistan
स्ट्रेटेजिक एरिया था। तो पाकिस्तान ने
along with China made a deal to
चाइना के साथ मिलके बलूचिस्तान में एक
build a port in Gwadar, an area in Balochistan.
एरिया है ग्वादर वहां पे पोर्ट बनाने की
Their plan was that this would
डील कर ली। इनका प्लान ये था कि एक तो ये
become an international trade hub.  Secondly,
इंटरनेशनल ट्रेड हब बनेगा। दूसरा इंडिया
this will make it easier for India to counter as well.
को भी काउंटर करने में इससे आसानी होगी।
But seeing all these things the Baloch were
लेकिन ये सारी चीजें देख के बलोच जो थे वो
becoming very frustrated.  He
एकदम फ्रस्ट्रेट होते जा रहे थे। उन्होंने
said that
कहा कि एक भी बलोचिस्तानी लीडर जो था उसको
without taking even a single Baloch leader into confidence, they started this Gadar Port
कॉन्फिडेंस में लिए बिना ये जो गदर पोर्ट
area in collaboration with the Chinese.  The
का जो एरिया है इसको चाइनीस के साथ मिलके
second thing that was done in this
इन्होंने स्टार्ट कर दिया। दूसरी चीज ये
deal was that in the jobs that were to be given,
जो डील करी इसमें जो जॉब होनी थी उसमें
instead of hiring people from the local Baloch community, Chinese and people from Pakistan’s Punjab
बजाय चाइनीस और पाकिस्तान के पंजाब
Province were hired.  On top of that, a
प्रोविंस के जो लोग थे उनको रखा गया। ऊपर
permanent settlement of the Army was made in this entire area.
से इस पूरे एरिया में आर्मी का परमानेंट
And some time before this,
सेटलमेंट कर दिया गया। और इससे कुछ टाइम
gold and copper were also found in Chagai district of Balochistan.  Reserves of 42 million tonnes were
में सोना और तांबा मिला था। 42 मिलियन टन
found.  Here too Pakistan
का रिजर्व मिले थे। यहां पे भी पाकिस्तान
worked in collaboration with Chinese engineers.
ने चाइनीस इंजीनियर्स के साथ मिलके काम
Whatever profit was made.
किया था। जितना प्रॉफिट हुआ था। उसमें से
China took 50% of that.  Pakistan took 48%
चाइना ने 50% लिया था। पाकिस्तान ने 48%
and Buchistan got only 2%.
लिया था और बूचिस्तान के पास सिर्फ 2% आया
Seeing all this, the Baloch became very
था। तो ये सब देख के बलोच जो थे वह बहुत
frustrated and the group they had
ज्यादा फ्रस्ट्रेट हो गए थे और इन्होंने
formed, BALA, carried out back to back attacks.  The
जो बीएएलए बनाई थी उसने बैक टू बैक हमले
workers working at Gwadar Port, the
किए। ग्वादर पोर्ट पे वहां के जो वर्कर
infrastructure there, the
काम कर रहे थे वहां का जो इंफ्रास्ट्रक्चर
gas pipeline and the Chinese workers were all
था गैस पाइपलाइन और जो चाइनीस वर्कर थे सब
attacked.  Later on C Pack was also
पे हमला किया। फिर आगे चलके सी पैक भी
started.  In this, Pakistan
शुरू किया गया। इसमें पाकिस्तान ने चाइनीस
along with the Chinese had invested 60 billion dollars.  The
के साथ मिलके इसमें 60 बिलियन डॉलर की
plan was to start
इन्वेस्टमेंट की थी। प्लान ये था कि चाइना
roads, railways, energy pipelines, fibre
तक रोड्स, रेलवे, एनर्जी पाइपलाइन, फाइबर
optics, special economic zones from China's Kajagar to Gwadar Port in Balochistan.
ऑप्टिक्स, स्पेशल इकोनॉमिक ज़ोन ये सारी
And it was said
चीजें स्टार्ट कर दी गई। और इसमें कहा गया
that Balochistan will now become Dubai.
कि बलोचिस्तान जो है अब वो दुबई बन जाएगा।
But here also the same problem was there.  Here
लेकिन यहां भी वही सेम प्रॉब्लम थी। यहां
also the Baloch were ignored.
पे भी जो बलोच थे उनको इग्नोर किया गया।
First, land was acquired from local Balochs for a low price.
पहले तो कम पैसों में जो लोकल बलोच थे
Instead of giving jobs to local people, Chinese were hired.
देने की बजाय चाइनीस रखे गए। पाकिस्तान के
People came from Punjab province of Pakistan.  A permanent army was
पंजाब प्रोविंस से लोग आए। परमानेंट आर्मी
maintained.  The fisherman was removed.  Whatever
रखी गई। फिशरमैन को हटा दिया गया। उनका जो
employment he had, he lost it all.  So this
रोजगार था वो भी सब चला गया। तो यह जो
entire Gwadar Port, CPEC and the whole
पूरा ग्वादर पोर्ट, सीपैक और यह सारा
system that was running, BLA,
सिस्टम जो चल रहा था बीएलए जो था उसने
did so much damage to CPEC that
सीपक पे इतना नुकसान किया कि आने वाले कई
so many Chinese were killed in Balochistan for many years to come.   The
सालों तक बलचिस्तान में इतने चाइनीज़ मारे।
situation had become such that China itself
हाल ये हो गया था कि चाइना ने खुद कहा के
said that if we have to complete this peace deal, then
कह दिया कि अगर हमें ये सीपक पूरा करना है
we will have to send our own army.  Now,
तो हमें अपनी ही आर्मी भेजनी होगी। अब
by 2018, the Baloch people who were fighting, had
2018 तक लड़ते-लते बलोच जो थे, उनको एक
understood one thing that by
चीज समझ में आ गई थी कि यह जो अलग-अलग
forming different groups, we are
ग्रुप बनाके हम अलग-अलग अपने-अपने
fighting for our own interests.  They are waging guerilla
इंटरेस्ट के लिए लड़ रहे हैं। गोरिल्ला
warfare.  This is only causing loss to us.
वॉरफेयर कर रहे हैं। इससे हमारा ही नुकसान
We should be united because we are demanding a separate
है। हमें एक होना चाहिए क्योंकि हम एक अलग
country so we should be united.
देश की मांग कर रहे हैं तो हमें एक होना
We should have a separate army.
चाहिए। हमारी अलग से एक आर्मी होनी चाहिए।
Only then will we be able to defeat Pakistan and
तभी हम पाकिस्तान को हरा के बलूचिस्तान को
separate Balochistan.  So what did they do?  B
अलग कर पाएंगे। तो इन्होंने क्या किया? बी
R A S Baloch Raji Ajoi Sanghat.
आर एएस बलोच राजी अजोई संघात।
Created a structure with this name.  Basically,
इस नाम से एक स्ट्रक्चर बनाया। बेसिकली
all the fighters from Balochistan, fighting
जितने भी बलूचिस्तान के फाइटर थे, लड़ाकू
groups, small people who were
ग्रुप्स थे, छोटे-छोटे लोग जो अलग ग्रुप
attacking Pakistan by forming separate groups,
बना के पाकिस्तान पे हमला कर रहे थे, इन
all of them were gathered together and
सबको इकट्ठा करके एक कोऑर्डिनेटेड तरीके
high profile attacks were carried out in a coordinated manner which caused a lot of
से हाई प्रोफाइल हमले किए जिससे काफी
damage.  The entire project of Seapack was
डैमेज हुआ। सारा सीपक का जो प्रोजेक्ट था,
put on hold by the Chinese in this attack.  And now, by the
के होल्ट पे डाल दिया। और अभी ये जो इसी
year 2025, after making these BRAS, these people have
साल 2025 आते-आते इन लोगों ने ये बीआरएएस
increased the frequency of attacks even more.  This year, this
ज्यादा बढ़ा दी है। इस साल इन्होंने ये जो
BRAS has formed the Baloch National
बीआरएएस है इन्होंने बलोच नेशनल
Army (BNA).  Considering itself as a
आर्मी बीएनए बनाई है। ये अपने आप को एक
country, it is fighting Pakistan like an army.
देश मान के एक आर्मी की तरह पाकिस्तान से
This BNA has caused a lot of damage.  A
लड़ रही है। इस बीएनए ने बहुत ही डैमेज
total of 72 coordinated attacks were carried out
किया है। टोटल 72 कोऑर्डिनेटेड हमले किए
on Pakistani forces.  Because of which it
पाकिस्तान फोर्सेस पे। जिसकी वजह से अब
no longer seems like some small
ऐसा नहीं लग रहा कि कोई छोटा-मोटा
guerilla warfare is going on.  It seems as
गोरिल्ला वॉरफेयर हो रहा है। ऐसा लग रहा
if the armies of two countries are fighting face to face.
है कि दो देशों की आर्मी आमने-सामने लड़
Just a few days ago, on 11 March
रही है। अभी थोड़े दिन पहले ही 11 मार्च
2025, Zafar Express train was going from Kota to Peshawar.  There
2025 कोटा से पेशावर जफर एक्सप्रेस ट्रेन
were 450 people.  As soon as the train
जा रही थी। 450 लोग थे। जैसे ही ट्रेन जो
reached Bolan Pass.  They had
थी वो बोलन पास के पास पहुंचती। इन्होंने
planted 8 KG IED bomb on the railway track
रेलवे ट्रैक पे 8 केजी आईडी बम लगा रखे थे
and as soon as the blast occurred the train derailed.
और ब्लास्ट होते ही ट्रेन ट्रैक से उतर
As soon as the train landed, BLA fighters took over the
गई। जैसे ही ट्रेन उतरी बीएलए के फाइटर ने
entire train.
पूरी ट्रेन पर कब्जा कर लिया। औरतें,
They left behind the women, children and the Baloch community
बच्चे और जो बलोच कम्युनिटी थी उनको छोड़
but took the rest captive and took over the entire
दिया लेकिन बाकियों को बंदी बनाकर पूरी
train.  Now when this
ट्रेन पे कब्जा कर लिया। अब जब ये
incident happened, Pakistan said that
इंसिडेंट हुआ तो पाकिस्तान ने कहा कि 48
our political prisoners should be released within 48 hours.
आवर्स में हमारे पॉलिटिकल प्रिजनर्स जो
But when they were not
हैं उनको छोड़ना चाहिए। लेकिन जब नहीं
released then Pakistan
छोड़े गए तो फिर पाकिस्तान ने ऑपरेशन
launched an operation.  The operation continued for a long time.  Then
लॉन्च किया। काफी टाइम तक ऑपरेशन चला। फिर
Pakistan said that 64 people lost their lives in this operation.
पाकिस्तान ने कहा कि इस ऑपरेशन में 64
BLA said that
लोगों की जान गई है। बीएलए ने कहा कि
they have killed more than 50 Pakistani army
इन्होंने पाकिस्तान के 50 से ज्यादा आर्मी
officers.  Now after this attack the
ऑफिसर मार दिए हैं। अब इस हमले के बाद से
situation has become much worse in this region.
हालत बहुत ज्यादा खराब हो गई इस रीजन में।
Security has been increased in this entire region.
इस पूरे रीजन के अंदर सिक्योरिटी बढ़ा दी
Pakistan has increased the presence of its army.
गई है। पाकिस्तान ने आर्मी की प्रेजेंस
Drones are flying throughout the area.
बढ़ा दी है। पूरे इलाके के अंदर ड्रोन उड़
And the biggest problem that has arisen for Pakistan at this time is
रहे हैं। और इस समय पाकिस्तान के लिए सबसे
that they are
बड़ी मुसीबत ये आकर खड़ी हो गई है कि उनको
not able to understand that they should
समझ में नहीं आ रहा है कि बलोचों से
fight the Balochs with weapons.  This should be done to stop them
हथियारों से लड़ाई की जाए। ऐसे करके रोका
or political dialogues should be held with them.
जाए या इनसे पॉलिटिकल डायलॉग्स किए जाए।
And along with this, many other equations are also
और इसके साथ-साथ इसमें कई और इक्वेशन भी
going on in it.  The strategic location of Balochistan is
चल रही हैं। बलूचिस्तान की जो स्ट्रेटेजिक
very important.  It
लोकेशन है वह बहुत इंपॉर्टेंट है। इसका
shares its border with Iran and Afghanistan.
बॉर्डर ईरान और अफगानिस्तान से लगता है।
Foreign players have also joined in this who are
इसमें फॉरेन प्लेयर्स भी आ चुके हैं जो
supporting Balochistan.  India and
बलूचिस्तान को सपोर्ट कर रहे हैं। इंडिया
Pakistan are already thirsty for each other's blood.
पाकिस्तान तो ऑलरेडी एक दूसरे के खून के
But USA's name is also coming up
प्यासे हैं। लेकिन यूएसए का भी नाम आ रहा
in this that
है इसमें कि ईरान और अफगानिस्तान को
Bhutistan will
काउंटर करने के लिए बूचिस्तान यूएस के लिए
become a very important player for the US to counter Iran and Afghanistan
एक बहुत ही इंपॉर्टेंट प्लेयर बन जाएगा
if it gets separated from Pakistan.  Now
अगर वो पाकिस्तान से अलग हो जाता है। अब
see what will happen next?  Only time
देखिए अभी आगे क्या होगा? ये तो टाइम ही
will tell.  But Pakistan has never been
बताएगा। लेकिन पाकिस्तान इस पर्टिकुलर
more troubled by the Balochs than it is at this particular time.
टाइम पे बलोचों से जितना ज्यादा परेशान
In the end let me
हुआ है उतना कभी नहीं हुआ है। लास्ट में
tell you once again that you
एक बार फिर से आपको बता दूं कि आउटस्किल
must do the two day A Master Program of Outskill.
का दो दिन का ए मास्टर प्रोग्राम जरूर
I have given you the link in the description.
करिए। लिंक मैंने आपको डिस्क्रिप्शन में
Thank you.
दे दिया है। थैंक यू।
[music]
[संगीत]